<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">On the Lord’s Prayer</title>
                <author xml:id="SP">Samuel Presbiter</author>
                <editor xml:id="AD">Andrew Dunning</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority><ref target="http://scholarlyediting.org">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</ref></authority>
                <idno type="file">deorationedominica.trans</idno>
                <idno type="edition">dequinqueseptenis-deorationedominica</idno>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name><ref target="http://cdrh.unl.edu">Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</ref></name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                        <repository>Pembroke College</repository>
                        <idno>115</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="41v"/>
            <lb/><head rend="red">On the Lord’s Prayer, that is to say the <quote>Our Father</quote>.</head>
            <lg n="1">
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-1.1">The prayer which Christ, praying, has taught</l>
                <note target="#DOD-1.2">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-1:210va[41]–210vb[6]">There are seven capital or principal vices, and from these rise all evils.
                        <lb/>These are the sources of the dark pit from which the waters of Babylon 
                        <lb/>flow and drops of iniquity pour, leading into every land.
                        <pb n="42r"/>
                        <lb/>The psalmist sings about these waters in the person of the faithful people,
                        <lb/>saying, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Ps.136.1">By the waters of Babylon</quote>, and so forth; <quote source="Bible.Vul:Ps.136.2">on the willows</quote>, and so forth.</seg> Of these vices,
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-2:210vb[12]–210vb[16]">three strip a person; the fourth <supplied reason="omitted" source="#DQS">whips the stripped; the fifth</supplied> drives out the whipped; the sixth 
                        <lb/>seduces the person driven out; the seventh subjects the seduced to slavery. 
                        <lb/>Pride takes God away from a person.</seg> <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-3:210vb[22]–210vb[25]">For pride is the love of one’s own status, 
                        <lb/>when a soul loves the good that it has on its own, that is, without him from whom 
                        <lb/>he accepted the good.</seg> <seg type="paraphrase" source="DQS#DOD-4:210vb[25]-210vb[29]">A small stream, cut off from its source, becomes dry; a ray of light, turned away from the enlightening sun,
                        <lb/>becomes dark.</seg> <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-5:210vb[37]–210vb[39]">For in the same way as every good is truly from God,
                        <lb/>just so can no good be had advantageously outside of God.</seg> <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-6:210vb[41]–211ra[7]">Whoever
                        <lb/>has not learned to love unless it is the good that he has in himself, while 
                        <lb/>he observes in another a good that he does not have, it is necessary that his own imperfection 
                        <lb/>torments him so bitterly that he does not love him in whom every good exists. And on that account, pride 
                        <lb/>always follows envy, because he who does not fasten love in that place where 
                        <lb/>every good exists is so wickedly elated with pride in himself that 
                        <lb/>he is painfully tormented by the good of another.</seg> <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-7:211ra[14]–211ra[20]">he does not even 
                        <lb/>judge the good of another to be detached from himself, if he loves his own in that place where
                        <lb/>he might possess at the same time the good of both himself and of another. As much, therefore, as he praises himself through pride outside of the creator, 
                        <lb/>so much does he fall under his neighbour through envy; and as much as 
                        <lb/>he is deceptively raised there, so much does he here truly cause himself to fall.</seg> Cum <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-8:211ra[21]–211rb[10]">envy has been born from pride,
                        <lb/>this breeds anger from itself – because the unhappy soul 
                        <lb/>is now angered on account of its own imperfection, since it does not delight 
                        <lb/>through charity in the good of another. And therefore it begins to be displeased even with what it has, 
                        <lb/>because it recognizes in another that which it cannot have. He therefore who 
                        <lb/>could have held the whole through charity, in God, loses even that which he attempts to have by pride outside of God 
                        <lb/>through envy and anger, because after he loses 
                        <lb/>God through pride, he loses his neighbour through envy, and through anger himself. 
                        <lb/>Because therefore, when everything is lost, nothing remains from which it can be glad, 
                        <lb/>the unhappy conscience is crushed in itself through sadness, 
                        <lb/>and since it has refused to delight in another’s good faithfully, it is rightly tormented by its own evil. 
                        <lb/>So after pride and envy and anger, which strip a person, sadness immediately 
                        <lb/>follows, which whips the stripped person. Greed approaches him next, 
                        <lb/>which drives out the whipped, because, when inward joy is lost, it drives him to seek consolation outside.
                        <lb/>Afterwards gluttony draws near, which seduces the person driven out, 
                        <lb/>because it attracts the soul desiring this vice by outer things in the first place, 
                        <lb/>as if tempting to excess from a neighbour – through natural desire itself.
                        <lb/>Finally comes lust, which violently subjects the seduced 
                        <lb/>to slavery, because after the flesh is set on fire through gluttony, 
                        <lb/>the weakened and 
                        <lb/>feebly determined soul cannot conquer the oncoming flame of passion. The mind has therefore been enslaved most savagely 
                        <lb/>to coercion, subdued in a disgraceful manner, and unless the requested goodness of the saviour 
                        <pb n="42v"/>
                        <lb/>brings relief, it will not now exist: so, serving captivity,
                        <lb/>its lost freedom may not be restored.</seg> <seg type="paraphrase" source="DQS#DOD-9a:211rb[11]">There are, therefore, seven requests</seg> in the Lord’s Prayer <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-9b:211rb[11]–211rb[12]">against seven
                        <lb/>vices.</seg> <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-10:211rb[21]–211rb[28]">Through pride therefore the heart is caused to swell; through envy it dries up; through anger it cracks; 
                        <lb/>through sadness it is crushed, and reduced as if to dust. Through greed 
                        <lb/>it is scattered; through gluttony it is infected, as if it is moistened; through lust 
                        <lb/>it is trampled and reduced to mud; so that the unhappy person 
                        <lb/>can now say, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Ps.68.3">I was stuck in the deep mire, and there is no substance.</quote></seg> He can be plucked out from this mud,
                    <lb/>shouting to God and devoutly asking his help. 
                    <lb/>From which this comes: <quote source="Bible.Vul:Ps.39.3"><seg xml:id="DOD-11">He heard my prayers and drew me out from a pit of wretchedness 
                            <lb/>and from the miry mud.</seg></quote>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-1.2">Contains five and two; by these seven evils are driven out,</l>
                <note target="#DOD-1.3">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-12:210va[21]–210va[24]">The spirit of the fear of the Lord; the spirit of godliness; the spirit of knowledge; the spirit 
                        <lb/>of strength; the spirit of counsel; the spirit of understanding; the spirit of wisdom.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-1.3">and seven good gifts are offered. From these arise</l>
                <note target="#DOD-1.4">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-13:210va[26]–210va[30]">Poverty of spirit, that is humility; graciousness or kindness; 
                        <lb/>remorse or sorrow; the hunger for righteousness or good desire; 
                        <lb/>mercy; cleanness of heart; peace.</seg> These seven virtues are noted
                    <lb/>in that Gospel: <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.5.1">Seeing the crowds, Jesus went up on the mountain</quote>, and so forth. 
                    <lb/>In that Gospel <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-14:210va[31]">seven beatitudes</seg> are also marked, namely these: <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-15:210va[31]–210va[34]">The kingdom
                        <lb break="no"/>of heaven; the possession of the land of the living; consolation; the satisfaction of righteousness;
                        <lb/>mercy; the vision of God; sonship of God.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-1.4">seven virtues; seven blessed gifts</l>
                <note target="#DOD-1.5">
                    <lb/>The evangelist: <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.10.22">The one who endures to the end will be saved.</quote>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-1.5">are gained by them, if one is firm in them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
                <note target="#DOD-2.1">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-16:211rb[40]–211va[3]">The first request is against pride, by which we say to God, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.6.9 Bible.Vul:Luke.11.2">Hallowed be your name.</quote>
                        <lb/>For we ask this so that he might allow us to fear his name
                        <lb/>and treat it as holy, so that we might be obedient to him through humility – we who have stepped forth through pride, 
                        <lb/>rebellious and insubordinate.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><milestone unit="lg" rend="enlarged paraph red"/><l xml:id="DOD-2.1">Pride is deadly – driven out by the first petition –</l>
                <note target="#DOD-2.2">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-17:210vb[15]–210vb[16]">Pride takes God away from a person.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-2.2">by which God is taken away from a person. And by the first request</l>
                <note target="#DOD-2.3">
                    <lb/>For the first <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-18:211va[3]–211va[8]">request the spirit of the fear of the Lord is given, so that he, coming to the heart, 
                        <lb/>might create in it the virtue of humility, which may heal the sickness of pride – 
                        <lb/>so that the humble person can come to the kingdom of heaven, which the arrogant angel 
                        <lb/>lost through pride.</seg>
                </note>
                <pb n="43r"/>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-2.3">the fear of the Lord is given. This makes us humble, and by these</l>
                <note target="#DOD-2.4">
                    <lb/>The evangelist: <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.5.3">Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</quote> <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.5.3">The poor 
                        <lb/>in spirit</quote>, that is the humble.
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-2.4">the kingdom of heaven is granted, and the blessed rejoice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
                <note target="#DOD-3.1">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-19:211va[8]–211va[17]">The second request is against envy, by which it is said, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.6.10">your kingdom come.</quote> 
                        <lb/>In fact, the kingdom of God is the salvation of mankind, because 
                        <lb/>God is said to reign in people at that moment when people themselves are subject to God, 
                        <lb/>at first devoting themselves to him through faith, and after clinging to him through sight. Who therefore 
                        <lb/>asks that the kingdom of God might come undoubtedly seeks the salvation of human beings. 
                        <lb/>And through this, while he asks for the common salvation of all, 
                        <lb/>he shows that he rejects the vice of envy.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><milestone unit="lg" rend="enlarged paraph blue"/><l xml:id="DOD-3.1">If the second request is made worthily, envy</l>
                <note target="#DOD-3.2a">
                    <lb/>Or <mentioned>driven away</mentioned>.
                </note>
                <note target="#DOD-3.2">
                    <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-20:210vb[16]–210vb[17]">Envy takes his neighbour from him.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-3.2">is then <seg xml:id="DOD-3.2a">put to flight</seg>; this is said to take away one’s neighbour.</l>
                <note target="#DOD-3.3">
                    <lb/>For the second <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-21:211va[18]–211va[21]">request the spirit of godliness is given, so that he, coming to the heart, 
                        <lb/>might kindle it to kindness, so that that person himself might reach the same possession of the eternal 
                        <lb/>inheritance to which he desires others 
                        <lb/>to reach.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-3.3">By this prayer devoutness is given, through which mildness is produced,</l>
                <note target="#DOD-3.4">
                    <lb/>The evangelist: <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.5.4">Blessed are the meek, for they shall inherit the earth.</quote>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-3.4">by which the land of the living may be given.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
                <note target="#DOD-4.1">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-22:211va[21]–211va[26]">The third request is against anger, by which it is said, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.6.10">Your will be done, 
                            <lb/>on earth as in heaven.</quote> For he does not wish to dispute who says, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.6.10">Your will be done</quote>, 
                        <lb/>but he proclaims that whatever the will of God should arrange pleases him, whether in himself 
                        <lb/>or in others, according to the judgement of his graciousness.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><milestone unit="lg" rend="enlarged paraph red"/><l xml:id="DOD-4.1">The third worthy request removes anger.</l>
                <note target="#DOD-4.2">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-23:210vb[17]">Anger takes a person from himself.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-4.2">This takes a person from himself; he is stripped from himself</l>
                <note target="#DOD-4.3">
                    <lb/>Since pride takes God away from a person, envy his neighbour, and anger himself,
                    <lb/>he is stripped.
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-4.3">when God is taken away, and his neighbour, and at the same time himself.</l>
                <note target="#DOD-4.4 #DOD-4.5">
                    <lb/>For the third <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-24:211va[27]–211va[34]">request, the spirit of knowledge is given, that he, coming to the heart, 
                        <lb/>might instruct and prick it in a manner beneficial to the soul, that the person might know the evil 
                        <lb/>which is allowed to come into being from his fault; and if he has had some good, that it comes from 
                        <lb/>the mercy of God. Through this, the spirit teaches him not to become angry against the creator, whatever he might endure in evil 
                        <lb/>or lack in goods, but 
                        <pb n="43v"/>
                        <lb/>to show his ability to tolerate adversity through everything.</seg> <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-25:211va[37]–211vb[3]"><quote source="Bible.Vul:Job.5.2">anger kills the foolish</quote>, when in adversities, 
                        <lb/>vexed and blinded through the intolerance of the vices, he either does not recognize that he has deserved the evil or
                        <lb/>that he accepted the good that he has through grace. The reward of consolation follows this virtue, that is 
                        <lb/>the prick of remorse or sorrow, so that whoever 
                        <lb/>voluntarily humbles himself here <supplied reason="explanation">on earth</supplied> before God through laments may deserve to find true joy 
                        <lb/>and happiness.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-4.4">Healthy knowledge is given by this prayer, though which</l>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-4.5">A prick of remorse comes forth in weeping, pleasing to salvation;</l>
                <note target="#DOD-4.6a">
                    <lb/>That is <mentioned>by a prick of remorse</mentioned>.
                </note>
                <note target="#DOD-4.6">
                    The evangelist: <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.5.5">Blessed are those who mourn, for they shall be comforted.</quote>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-4.6"><seg xml:id="DOD-4.6a">by this</seg> great heavenly consolation is bestowed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
                <note target="#DOD-5.1">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-26:211vb[4]–211vb[10]">The fourth request is against sadness, by which it is said, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.6.11 Bible.Vul:Luke.11.3">Give us today our daily bread.</quote> 
                        <lb/>For sadness is weariness of the soul with grief, when the mind 
                        <lb/>does not desire inward goods, caused to become dispirited in a certain way, and made bitter by its vice; 
                        <lb/>and with all its liveliness dead, it does not become happy at any desire of spiritual restoration.</seg>
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-27:210vb[17]–210vb[18]">Sadness whips the stripped person.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><milestone unit="lg" rend="enlarged paraph red"/><l xml:id="DOD-5.1">The fourth petition puts sadness to flight; this whips</l>
                <note target="#DOD-5.2 #DOD-5.3">
                    <lb/>For the fourth <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-28:211vb[15]–211vb[22]">request the spirit of strength is given, that it may lift up the weary spirit, 
                        <lb/>in order that, when it has recovered that virtue of its former strength, it might recover from 
                        <lb/>the weakness of its weariness to the desire of inward taste. The spirit of strength accordingly creates 
                        <lb/>in the heart a hunger for righteousness, so that who is here <supplied reason="explanation">on earth</supplied> intensely kindled through the desire 
                        <lb/>for devoutness may pursue full abundance to that place <supplied reason="explanation">in heaven</supplied> 
                        <lb/>for the reward of blessedness.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-5.2">the stripped person. The spirit of strength is received by this prayer;</l>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-5.3">the good hunger for righteousness is brought out from that source,</l>
                <note target="#DOD-5.4">
                    <lb/>The evangelist: <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.5.6">Blessed are those who hunger and thirst for righteousness, for they 
                        <lb/>shall be satisfied.</quote>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-5.4">through which the righteous are sated with full joy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
                <note target="#DOD-6.1">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-29:211vb[23]–211vb[30]">The fifth request is against greed, by which it is said, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.6.12">Forgive us our debts, 
                            <lb/>as we also have forgiven our debtors.</quote> For it is right that when a debt is to be paid back, 
                        <lb/>he should not be anxious who refused to be bitter in demanding its payment. 
                        <lb/>And for that reason, when the vice of greed is taken from us through the grace of God, it is given in such a manner that 
                        <lb/>we should be absolved from our debt, by the terms of salvation set in place.</seg> 
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-30a:210vb[18]">Greed drives out</seg> the stripped and <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-30b:210vb[18]">whipped</seg> person.
                </note>
                <lb/><milestone unit="lg" rend="enlarged paraph blue"/><l xml:id="DOD-6.1">The fifth request pushes out greed;</l>
                <note target="#DOD-6.2 #DOD-6.3">
                    <lb/>For the fifth <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-31:211vb[30]–211vb[34]">request, the spirit of counsel is given, who teaches us in this world 
                        <pb n="44r"/>
                        <lb/>to pay attention to our sins willingly, so that in the future, 
                        <lb/>when we deliver an account for our sins, we will deserve
                        <lb/>to find mercy.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-6.2">this drives out the despoiled person. Then the spirit of counsel is given:</l>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-6.3">this makes people pity their brothers.</l>
                <note target="#DOD-6.4a">
                    <lb/>That is <mentioned>to the merciful</mentioned>.
                </note>
                <note target="#DOD-6.4">
                    The evangelist: <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.5.6">Blessed are
                        <lb/>the merciful, for they shall receive mercy.</quote>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-6.4">A great reward, heavenly mercy, is entrusted <seg xml:id="DOD-6.4a">to them</seg>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
                <note target="#DOD-7.1">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-32:211vb[34]–212ra[3]">The sixth request is against gluttony, by which it is said, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.6.13 Bible.Vul:Luke.11.4" xml:id="DQS-Matt6.13a" next="#DQS-Matt6.13b">Lead us not</quote>, that is, do not allow us to be led, 
                        <lb/><quote xml:id="DQS-Matt6.13b" prev="#DQS-Matt6.13a">into temptation.</quote> This is the temptation by which the pleasures of the flesh 
                        <lb/>often strive to pull us to excess through natural desire, and secretly 
                        <lb/>put pleasure under their control, while openly speaking smoothly about their necessity to us. 
                        <lb/>Assuredly, we will then by no means be led into this temptation if we strive 
                        <lb/>to pay attention to the assistance of nature, following the limit of necessity, so that 
                        <lb/>we will always remember to restrain the appetite from the pleasures of delight.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><milestone unit="lg" rend="enlarged paraph red"/><l xml:id="DOD-7.1">The sixth request is said to attack gluttony; this</l>
                <note target="#DOD-7.2">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-33:210vb[19]">Gluttony seduces the person driven out.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-7.2">wickedly seduces the person driven out. For this worthy prayer</l>
                <note target="#DOD-7.3">
                    <lb/>For the sixth request <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-34:212ra[4]–212ra[15]">the spirit of understanding is given to us who ask for it, so that the inward restoration 
                        <lb/>of the word of God might restrain outward desire, and that bodily need might neither have the strength to crush the mind strengthened by spiritual food, 
                        <lb/>nor to overcome the desire of the flesh. 
                        <lb/>For this reason indeed the Lord himself responded to his tempter, while 
                        <lb/>he was making a false hint about the refreshment of outward bread, saying, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.4.4">One does not live by bread alone, 
                            <lb/>but by every word that comes from the mouth of God</quote>, so that he might openly show that when the mind is restored with that bread inwardly, 
                        <lb/>it does not particularly care if the flesh should 
                        <lb/>outwardly undergo hunger for a time.</seg>
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-35:212ra[23]–212ra[24]">From the spirit of understanding, cleanness of the heart is born.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-7.3">the spiritus of understanding is given; it creates cleanness.</l>
                <note target="#DOD-7.4">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-36:212ra[24]–212ra[26]">For cleanness of heart, the vision of God is promised. As it is written, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.5.8">Blessed are the clean 
                            <lb/>in heart, for they will see God.</quote></seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-7.4">By this virtue, the blessed vision of God is granted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
                <note target="#DOD-8.1">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-37:212ra[26]">The seventh petition is against lust, by which it is said, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.6.13">Deliver us from evil.</quote></seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><milestone unit="lg" rend="enlarged paraph blue"/><l xml:id="DOD-8.1">The seventh worthy request is said to remove lust;</l>
                <note target="#DOD-8.2">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-38:210vb[19]–210vb[20]">Lust subjects the seduced to slavery.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-8.2">this subjects the seduced person, that he may be</l>
                <note target="#DOD-8.3">
                    <lb/>For the seventh <seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-39:212ra[29]–212ra[42]">request the spirit of wisdom is given, which restores the lost freedom to the prisoner, 
                        <pb n="44v"/>
                        <lb/>and through grace he escapes the yoke of sinful coercion, which he did not 
                        <lb/>have the strength to accomplish by his own means. <mentioned>Wisdom</mentioned> (<foreign xml:lang="la">sapientia</foreign>), indeed, is so called from <mentioned>taste</mentioned> (<foreign xml:lang="la">sapor</foreign>). The mind, 
                        <lb/>touched by the flavour of inward sweetness, gathers its whole self within through desire, 
                        <lb/>and it is never weakly loosened externally in the pleasure of the flesh, 
                        <lb/>because it holds everything within in which it delights. Sweetness within, therefore, is fittingly placed against external 
                        <lb/>pleasure, so that however much more it may have begun to taste 
                        <lb/>and be pleased, so much more freely and willingly may this be despised; 
                        <lb/>the mind, finally made peaceful in itself as long as there is nothing it may desire externally, 
                        <lb/>rests within, complete, through love.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-8.3">a slave. Spiritual wisdom is given</l>
                <note target="#DOD-8.4 #DOD-8.5 #DOD-8.6 #DOD-8.7">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-40:212ra[42]–212rb[7]">The spirit of wisdom, touching the heart with its sweetness,
                        <lb/>both regulates the flame of external desire, 
                        <lb/>and creates inward peace when it numbs lust, so that while the mind is entirely gathered to inward joy, 
                        <lb/>a person may fully and completely be restored to the image of God, as it is written, <quote source="Bible.Vul:Matt.5.9">Blessed are the peacemakers, 
                            <lb/>for they shall be called sons of God.</quote></seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-8.4">for this prayer: wisdom quells passion for the external</l>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-8.5">and creates peace within, when the wicked movements are put to sleep,</l>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-8.6">and thus the person is restored. Peace makes him so that he may be</l>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-8.7">a true son of God, when heavenly peace is gathered.</l>
                <note target="#DOD-8.8 #DOD-8.9 #DOD-8.10">
                    <lb/><seg type="q" source="DQS#DOD-41:210va[35]–210va[40]">Understand vices themselves as if are were certain sicknesses of the soul, or wounds of the inner 
                        <lb/>person. The very person, indeed, is like a patient; God, the physician; the gifts 
                        <lb/>of the Holy Spirit, the remedy; the virtues, healings; the beatitudes, the joy 
                        <lb/>of happiness.</seg>
                </note>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-8.8">The Lord puts to flight the sicknesses of the inner person;</l>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-8.9">by remedies of this kind he makes him strong in virtue.</l>
                <lb/><l xml:id="DOD-8.10">And when he speaks well, he gathers the blessed joys.</l>
            </lg>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
