<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Hugh of St Victor’s <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> (<title>On the Five Sevens</title>) and its Versification in Samuel Presbiter’s <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> (<title>On the Lord’s Prayer</title>)</title>
                <author>Andrew Dunning</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority><ref target="http://scholarlyediting.org">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</ref></authority>
                <idno type="file">intro.dequinqueseptenis-deorationedominica</idno>
                <idno type="edition">dequinqueseptenis-deorationedominica</idno>
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name><ref target="http://cdrh.unl.edu">Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</ref></name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2016</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International license.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>
                </respStmt>
                <idno type="vol">37</idno>
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In a casual conversation on medieval theology, the seven deadly sins are among the topics most likely to arise. Hugh of St Victor’s <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> (<title>On the Five Sevens</title>) is a letter addressed to an unknown monastic showing how this widely known but insufficiently understood scheme was applied in the high medieval period. Hugh links the vices with four other groups of seven: the requests of the Lord’s Prayer (using the version in Matthew 6:9–13), the gifts of the Holy Spirit (based on Isaiah 11:2–3), the virtues, and the beatitudes (Matt. 5:3–9).<ptr target="#note1" xml:id="nr1" n="1"/> Its accessibility and consistent schematization made it appealing to anyone wishing to teach these subjects, and it was widely copied for the remainder of the Middle Ages.<ptr target="#note2" xml:id="nr2" n="2"/> Later writers also adapted its contents to present it in new ways, of which Samuel Presbiter’s <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> is one such example, written around the turn of the thirteenth century.</p>
                <p><title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> has been printed many times; this article presents a documentary edition of Paris, Bibliothèque Mazarine, MS 717, representing the edition of Abbot Gilduin made shortly after Hugh’s death. <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> has never been studied or published, and survives in a single manuscript from Bury St Edmunds that was likely corrected by its author, now Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115. Both works are here presented for the first time with an English translation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Hugh of St Victor</head>
                <p>Hugh of St Victor (ca. 1096–1141) was an Augustinian regular canon at the Abbey of Saint Victor in Paris.<ptr target="#note3" xml:id="nr3" n="3"/> He is best known for his <title xml:lang="la">Didascalicon</title>, an introduction to the art and purpose of reading,<ptr target="#note4" xml:id="nr4" n="4"/> <title xml:lang="la">De sacramentis</title> (<title>On the Sacraments</title>), a forerunner to the systematizing <foreign xml:lang="la">summae</foreign> of the scholastic theologians,<ptr target="#note5" xml:id="nr5" n="5"/> and his innovative use of Noah’s Ark as a teaching aid.<ptr target="#note6" xml:id="nr6" n="6"/> Unlike many medieval authors, he has been read continuously since his own time, with his works successfully navigating manuscript transmission, the printing press, and modernism. This success can be attributed in part to an organization that provided sustained promotion for his work – the Augustinian abbey of Saint Victor in Paris, founded in Hugh’s youth and surviving until its destruction during the French Revolution. The realization that our understanding of Hugh cannot be separated from his institutional context has produced something of a renaissance in studies on the Victorines and their school.<ptr target="#note7" xml:id="nr7" n="7"/></p>
                <div>
                    <head>
                        <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title>
                    </head>
                    <p><title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> is thought to have been written ca. 1130/31–1137.<ptr target="#note8" xml:id="nr8" n="8"/> It presents itself as a letter to an anonymous fellow monastic, responding to a specific request for an explanation of five groups of seven phenomena Hugh identifies in scripture. It is difficult to deduce anything concerning the situation in which this arose: nothing in the tone indicates whether it was a topic that arose in casual conversation with a friend, or an enquiry from a distant correspondent pressing for further detail on the subject. Roger Baron suggests that the letter was a logical outgrowth from Hugh’s earlier work <title xml:lang="la">De institutione nouitiorum</title>.<ptr target="#note9" xml:id="nr9" n="9"/> The essay is an effective and focused tool for teaching and internalizing a small but practical aspect of salvation.</p>
                    <p>Hugh presents the five identified groups of seven as having an integral and logical relationship both within their own families and with the others, the vices successively breaking apart the person, which only God can amend.<ptr target="#note10" xml:id="nr10" n="10"/> While Hugh claims that his subjects come from scripture, this is only loosely true of the vices, which occur in scripture but not together: their assembly is the result of a longer tradition beginning with Evagrius Ponticus and John Cassian.<ptr target="#note11" xml:id="nr11" n="11"/> The approach of taking the vices as a connected whole, popularized by Gregory the Great, is now termed the <q>concatenation</q> model,<ptr target="#note12" xml:id="nr12" n="12"/> and Hugh reused it in later works.<ptr target="#note13" xml:id="nr13" n="13"/> Each of the vices is a direct result of the one preceding it, with pride as the root of them all and lust as their end, in a list that differed slightly from earlier inventories:<ptr target="#note14" xml:id="nr14" n="14"/></p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Superbia</foreign>/Pride</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Inuidia</foreign>/Envy</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Ira</foreign>/Anger</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Tristitia</foreign>/Sadness</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Auaritia</foreign>/Greed</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Gula</foreign>/Gluttony</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Luxuria</foreign>/Lust</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>In the meantime, the seven requests of the Lord’s Prayer directly combat the vices (Matt. 6:9–13):</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Sanctificetur nomen tuum</foreign>/Hallowed be your name</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Adueniat regnum tuum</foreign>/Your kingdom come</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Fiat uoluntas tua sicut in caelo et in terra</foreign>/Your will be done, on earth as in heaven</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Panem nostrum cotidianum da nobis hodie</foreign>/Give us today our daily bread</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Dimitte nobis debita nostra sicut et nos dimittimus debitoribus nostris</foreign>/Forgive us our debts, as we also have forgiven our debtors</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Ne nos inducas in temptationem</foreign>/Lead us not into temptation</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Libera nos a malo</foreign>/Deliver us from evil</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>In response to these, God provides seven gifts of the Holy Spirit, from Isaiah 11:2–3:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Spiritus timoris domini</foreign>/Spirit of the fear of the Lord</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Spiritus pietatis</foreign>/Spirit of godliness</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Spiritus scientiae</foreign>/Spirit of knowledge</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Spiritus fortitudinis</foreign>/Spirit of strength</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Spiritus consilii</foreign>/Spirit of counsel</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Spiritus intellectus</foreign>/Spirit of understanding</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Spiritus sapientiae</foreign>/Spirit of wisdom</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>These produce seven virtues, based on the Sermon on the Mount, Matthew 5:3–9:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Paupertas spiritus</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="la">humilitas</foreign>)/Poverty of spirit (humility)</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Mansuetudo</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="la">benignitas</foreign>)/Graciousness (kindness)</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Compunctio</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="la">dolor</foreign>)/Remorse (sorrow)</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Esuries iustitiae</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="la">desiderium bonum</foreign>)/Hunger for justice (good desire)</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Misericordia</foreign>/Mercy</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Munditia cordis</foreign>/Cleanness of heart</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Pax</foreign>/Peace</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Finally, these result in the corresponding beatitudes of the same passage from Matthew:</p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Regnum caelorum</foreign>/Kingdom of heaven</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Possessio terrae uiuentium</foreign>/Possession of the land of the living</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Consolatio</foreign>/Consolation</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Iustitiae saturitas</foreign>/Satisfaction of justice</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Misericordia</foreign>/Mercy</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Visio dei</foreign>/Vision of God</item>
                        <item><foreign xml:lang="la">Filiatio dei</foreign>/Sonship of God</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Most readers would likely count eight or nine beatitudes in the Sermon on the Mount (Matt. 5:3–12): Hugh’s numeration of seven follows Augustine in <title xml:lang="la">De sermo domini in monte</title> (<title>On the Sermon of the Lord on the Mount</title>), who argues that the eighth beatitude is merely a summary of the first seven; the ninth is not to be taken with the rest, since it dispenses with the impersonal construction and there is no specific blessing.<ptr target="#note15" xml:id="nr15" n="15"/> He links these directly to the gifts of the Holy Spirit.<ptr target="#note16" xml:id="nr16" n="16"/> It is only natural that when he reaches the Lord’s Prayer in his discussion of the Sermon on the Mount, he also links these petitions to his seven beatitudes.<ptr target="#note17" xml:id="nr17" n="17"/> Four of the five groups Hugh discusses had a precedent. It has been noted that he might also have been inspired by one of the versions of the <title>Glosa</title> on Matthew, most versions of which reflect Augustine’s approach,<ptr target="#note18" xml:id="nr18" n="18"/> but Hugh almost certainly had direct access to Augustine’s work, since the abbey owned a copy written in the early twelfth century.<ptr target="#note19" xml:id="nr19" n="19"/></p>
                    <p>While Hugh’s use of numbers might seem artificial to a modern audience – Hauréau, an influential nineteenth-century commentator on Hugh, derided him as <q>le Pythagore des théologiens</q><ptr target="#note20" xml:id="nr20" n="20"/> – their deployment as a mnemonic was common in the Middle Ages. Far from perfunctorily using numbers, Hugh applied them in a particularly practical and rigorous manner for improving the memory. In <title xml:lang="la">De tribus maximis circumstantiis gestorum</title>, he encouraged students to use numbers mapped onto a grid to promote a spacial understanding of a subject, a particularly innovative and effective approach.<ptr target="#note21" xml:id="nr21" n="21"/></p>
                    <p>Hugh left a clear system for remembering and applying five of the key medieval devotional schemes, and it gained new relevance with the rise of new texts for pastoral care leading up to and following the Fourth Lateran Council.<ptr target="#note22" xml:id="nr22" n="22"/> With this, Hugh’s text was supplied with new visual and oral methods for presenting and memorizing its contents. Samuel Presbiter’s <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> is one example of a paraphrase to promote memorization. One also finds a series of circular diagrams or <foreign xml:lang="la">rotae</foreign> that originated in the late twelfth century, some translated into the vernacular, some of which were directly influenced by Hugh;<ptr target="#note23" xml:id="nr23" n="23"/> one called by scholars the <title>Septenarium pictum</title> survives in at least a dozen copies.<ptr target="#note24" xml:id="nr24" n="24"/> These acted as a supplement to Hugh’s text rather than replacing it, and new manuscript copies continued to be made until the end of the medieval period. The influence of <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> can be traced even in Thomas Aquinas,<ptr target="#note25" xml:id="nr25" n="25"/> and it continued to appeal to the reformers of the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries.<ptr target="#note26" xml:id="nr26" n="26"/></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Abbot Gilduin’s Edition of Hugh and Paris, Bibliothèque Mazarine, MS 717</head>
                    <p>It is possible that <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> might not have circulated much further than its original recipient were it not for an edition created of Hugh’s works after his death in 1141 by Abbot Gilduin.<ptr target="#note27" xml:id="nr27" n="27"/> The existence of this effort and its results are documented by the <title>Indiculum</title> listing Hugh’s works in Oxford, Merton College, MS 49, where <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> is mentioned under that title.<ptr target="#note28" xml:id="nr28" n="28"/> It has become increasingly apparent that this edition was enormously influential in establishing the form and contents of Hugh’s corpus, and in promoting its dissemination. It is also a useful basis for understanding Hugh’s thought within his historical context. Paul Rorem has written a successful introduction to Hugh by working through his major works in the order they appear in the <title>Indiculum</title>.<ptr target="#note29" xml:id="nr29" n="29"/> An effort is now underway to recreate the text of this edition.<ptr target="#note30" xml:id="nr30" n="30"/></p>
                    <p>One of the most important textual witnesses to <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> is a source contemporary with Gilduin: Paris, Bibliothèque Mazarine, MS 717. It originally belonged to the Abbey of Saint Victor, appearing in the sixteenth-century catalogue by Claude de Grandrue.<ptr target="#note31" xml:id="nr31" n="31"/> Baron noted its correlation with the <title>Indiculum</title>,<ptr target="#note32" xml:id="nr32" n="32"/> but he and other earlier commentators believed that the book was from the early thirteenth century.<ptr target="#note33" xml:id="nr33" n="33"/> More recently, Patricia Stirnemann dated it palaeographically to 1141–50.<ptr target="#note34" xml:id="nr34" n="34"/> Poirel argues that it was a direct copy from the original manuscripts produced under Gilduin, providing a full codicological description,<ptr target="#note35" xml:id="nr35" n="35"/> and Stammberger compares it extensively with the <title>Indiculum</title>.<ptr target="#note36" xml:id="nr36" n="36"/></p>
                    <p>The text of <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> found on fols. 210va–212rb is written in a single protogothic hand. The scribe usually joins prepositions such as <q>ab</q> to the following word. The text is moderately abbreviated, but the scribe usually writes out <q>anima</q> and <q>dominus</q> rather than using the standard contractions. It is contained within a single gathering: the catchword on fol. 211v was used for assembling the gathering, and does not indicate its end.<ptr target="#note37" xml:id="nr37" n="37"/> It opens with a blue two-line capital, with red tracery. A small amount of red ink matching the shade of the initial on fol. 212rb has been spilled on fol. 211ra. It has been corrected by at least one reader, distinguished by a hand with thin strokes. This might be a contemporary corrector working with the scribe, as most of the ninth line on fol. 211rb (beginning <q>subueniat saluatoris</q>) has been erased and rewritten in what appears to be the same hand, compressed in order to fit into the limited space. One paragraph mark has been added in the margin in plummet on fol. 210vb, dividing what could be conceived as the introduction from the rest of the work. A later annotator (designated B in the edition) has added six inline paragraph marks in addition to running labels in the margins highlighting the numbers in the text, and flags several key passages with a set of three dots and a vertical line.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Editing <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title></head>
                    <p><title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> was first printed in 1474 or slightly earlier.<ptr target="#note38" xml:id="nr38" n="38"/> It was published by Stephanus in 1506,<ptr target="#note39" xml:id="nr39" n="39"/> breaking the work somewhat arbitrarily into four chapters. It was edited only in part, as <title xml:lang="la">Annotationes elucidatoriae testamenti noui</title> 2.15, in the collections of Hugh’s works published in 1526 and 1648.<ptr target="#note40" xml:id="nr40" n="40"/> In 1836, it was published as <title xml:lang="la">S. Augustini Epistola de septem petitionibus in Pater noster</title>, with the editors arguing for the attribution on the basis of its similarity to Augustine’s <title xml:lang="la">De sermone domini in monte</title> 2.38.<ptr target="#note41" xml:id="nr41" n="41"/> It appeared in the Patrologia Latina (PL) series as <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis seu septenariis opusculum</title><ptr target="#note42" xml:id="nr42" n="42"/> with Hugh’s <title xml:lang="la">De septem donis spiritus sancti</title> added as a fifth chapter.<ptr target="#note43" xml:id="nr43" n="43"/> It was most recently published by Baron in a critical edition using seven manuscripts, taking the Mazarine manuscript as a base text.<ptr target="#note44" xml:id="nr44" n="44"/></p>
                    <p>Baron’s apparatus does not accurately report variants from the Mazarine manuscript: he indicates that it reads <q>ad inuicem</q> at fol. 210va rather than <q>abinuicem</q> (a variant he ascribes only to Va), <q>ipsi</q> (the reading of the PL) at fol. 211ra rather than <q>sibi</q> (not reported as a variant), and <q>docetur</q> at fol. 211vb rather than <q>donatur</q> (which he ascribes only to Va, H, and L). He arbitrarily classicizes many spellings. While his text superficially follows the punctuation of the manuscript, he freely modifies it, often detrimentally: for instance, on fol. 210vb, the sentence <q>Cur nisi … amittat</q> ends not with Baron’s question mark but more correctly with a simple <foreign xml:lang="la">punctus</foreign>; Hugh has finished his interrogation of pride, and is now stating the force of its destruction. The edition was published posthumously,<ptr target="#note45" xml:id="nr45" n="45"/> and some of these errors might not have occurred had Baron lived to see it through the press. While his choice of manuscript is good, it has more unique and potentially correct readings than he shows.</p>
                    <p>The present edition emends the manuscript only where required for sense. Only a few significant modifications to the text are necessary. At fol. 210vb, <q>se</q> is suppressed in <q>ab illuminante se auertitur</q>, reported by Baron as occurring only in the Mazarine manuscript. While it can be found in at least one other witness,<ptr target="#note46" xml:id="nr46" n="46"/> the usage of the previous sentence indicates that this is an error. At fol. 211ra, <q>quatum</q> is replaced with <q>quantum</q>, and at fol. 211va, <q>uenerati</q> with <q>uenerari</q>: these corrections are also made by Baron but not reported. Prepositions are separated where appropriate in the regularized form of the edition.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Samuel Presbiter</head>
                <p>Samuel Presbiter (fl. 1200) is known to history only through the preservation of his works in two volumes from the abbey library of Bury St Edmunds, now Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115 and Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS Bodley 860 (<title>SC</title> 2723). His writings largely excerpt and versify earlier prose works. <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> is a versification of Hugh’s <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title>. Extracts from Hugh’s prose are copied between the verses as a commentary, a format Samuel uses in several of his works. The change in title reflects a shift in focus. While the verses summarize each of the groups of five, there is a stronger focus on the Lord’s Prayer, and its worthy (<foreign xml:lang="la">digna</foreign>) invocation. The result is an epitome of Hugh’s work, removing the frame of a letter, presenting the source material from the Sermon on the Mount more explicitly, and providing a series of verses that could be memorized in order to recall the full contents of the whole.</p>
                <p>All that is certainly known of Samuel’s life is his claim to have studied under William de Montibus, who taught at the cathedral school in Lincoln from the 1180s until some point before his death in 1213.<ptr target="#note47" xml:id="nr47" n="47"/> There are only a few possible references to him in documentary sources; he might be identifiable with the <q>Samuel de Ounebi</q> (Owmby by Spital, in Lincolnshire) who witnessed a charter alongside William de Montibus between 1196 and 1203.<ptr target="#note48" xml:id="nr48" n="48"/> A <q>mansionem Samuelis</q> is recorded in Owmby by Spital around 1200–1210.<ptr target="#note49" xml:id="nr49" n="49"/> The name Presbiter, which is unusual but attached to others in the city of Lincoln, was sometimes used to translate the name <q>Cohen</q>, leading to a suggestion that Samuel may have been a Jewish convert, or from a family of converts.<ptr target="#note50" xml:id="nr50" n="50"/> Given that both of the manuscripts containing Samuel’s works are from Bury St Edmunds, the author might also have been associated with the abbey, which fostered a community of learning under Samson, abbot from 1182 until 1211.<ptr target="#note51" xml:id="nr51" n="51"/></p>
                <p><title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> is likely one of Samuel’s earlier works. He labels most of his writings <q>collecta</q> (<q>things gathered</q> or <q>compiled</q>), most combining verses with a prose commentary. Two works, probably his earliest, are entirely in prose:<ptr target="#note52" xml:id="nr52" n="52"/></p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item><title xml:lang="la">Collecta ex auditis super psalmos in scola magistri Willelmi de Monte</title>/<title>Things gathered from things heard on the Psalms in the school of master William de Montibus</title> (Bodley 860, fols. 9r–93v), an incomplete commentary on the Psalms<ptr target="#note53" xml:id="nr53" n="53"/></item>
                    <item><title xml:lang="la">Collecta ex speculo beati Gregorii sine uersibus</title>/<title>Things gathered from the Speculum of blessed Gregory, without verses</title> (Pembroke College 115, fols. 47r–77r)</item>
                </list>
                <p>In most of his works, both verses and prose were copied together, the prose often an extract from another work to show precisely what Samuel is versifying, and written directly above the verses to which it applies. These include:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item><title xml:lang="la">Collecta ex diuersis auditis in scola magistri Willelmi de Monte</title>/<title>Things gathered from various things heard in the school of master William de Montibus</title> (Bodley 860, fols. 94r–107v)</item>
                    <item><title xml:lang="la">Collecta ex speculo beati Gregorii cum uersibus</title>/<title>Things gathered from the Speculum of blessed Gregory, with verses</title> (Pembroke College 115, fols. 1r–41v)</item>
                    <item>the present work, <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title>/<title>On the Lord’s Prayer</title> (Pembroke College 115, fols. 41v–44v)</item>
                    <item>four short compositions (Pembroke College 115, fols. 45r–46r), with the incipits:
                        <list type="ordered"><item><q>Est proprium domini mentem bene pacificare</q> (8 lines)</item><item><q>Est uagus hic cuius animus non recta cupiscit</q> (2 lines)</item><item><q>Flos bonus est actus hoc est spes fulgor odorque</q> (12 lines)</item><item><q>Multiplex hominis pacientia dicitur esse</q>, entitled <q>De patientia</q> (2 lines)</item></list></item>
                </list>
                <p>In two works that are probably among his latest, the verses stand on their own, with glosses added in the margins:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item><title xml:lang="la">Collecta ad habendam memoriam quorumdam utilium in sacra scriptura</title>/<title>Things gathered for remembering various useful things in sacred scripture</title> (Bodley 860, fols. 108r–206v)<ptr target="#note54" xml:id="nr54" n="54"/></item>
                    <item>a verse paraphrase of Psalm 1 (Bodley 860, fols. 1r–8v)<ptr target="#note55" xml:id="nr55" n="55"/></item>
                </list>
                <p>The only overt indicators of chronology for these works are that <title xml:lang="la">Ex auditis super psalmos</title> and <title xml:lang="la">Ex diuersis auditis</title> reflect Samuel’s studies under William de Montibus, while <title xml:lang="la">Ad habendam memoriam</title> was written after he left the school, according to the extended heading with which the work begins. The two <title xml:lang="la">Ex speculo</title> works abridge the <title xml:lang="la">Speculum Gregorii</title>, Adalbert of Metz’s epitome of Gregory the Great’s <title xml:lang="la">Moralia in Iob</title>;<ptr target="#note56" xml:id="nr56" n="56"/> many copies of it existed in England, including one at Bury St Edmunds by the late twelfth century.<ptr target="#note57" xml:id="nr57" n="57"/> Samuel also refers to it in his paraphrase of Psalm 1 (for example, Bodley 860, fols. 4r, 5r) and <title xml:lang="la">Ad habendam memoriam</title> (fols. 128v, 130r). These works are also his most mature: the marginal glosses reflect increased confidence to work directly with biblical texts as well as secondary theological works, and often amalgamate references to many titles rather than summarize a single source.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>
                        <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>The verses of <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> are written in hexameter and organized into eight stanzas: one introductory, and one for each of the requests in the Lord’s Prayer. These summarize the entirety of Hugh’s system of five groups, typically beginning with an indication of which vice the request addresses, followed by the gift of the Holy Spirit given in response, the corresponding virtue that comes from this, and the resulting beatitude. In Samuel’s other writings, verses are frequently presented to be memorized in order to learn the details of a particular concept, and the intent is presumably the same for this work.</p>
                    <p>As the title suggests, Samuel shifts the primary focus to the Lord’s Prayer, with a subtle reforming stance. Hugh presents the prayer as the first step towards their elimination, and arguably the only one for which humans are truly responsible: but he begins with the vices, which rhetorically puts the emphasis on understanding the effects of the vices and how one might rid oneself of them. Samuel introduces a new emphasis in his verses: that the prayer must be <foreign xml:lang="la">digna</foreign>, <q>worthy</q> or <q>appropriate</q>. When a person presents the prayer, everything else follows naturally, as long as it is done wholeheartedly and solemnly. <q>Et bene sonato felicia gaudia confert</q> (fol. 44v) – <q>And when he speaks well, he gathers the blessed joys.</q></p>
                    <p>The commentary to the verses is a direct abridgement of <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title>, reorganizing the text to made it and adding in quotations of the Beatitudes. Samuel eliminates most of the details of the discussion concerning the effects of the vices, although after quoting Hugh’s basic definitions of their correlation, these are repeated throughout the text for easier reference above the corresponding verse. The emphasis is placed on understanding the practical workings of the Lord’s Prayer, and not on the effects of vice, which are arguably much more visible. Connecting words such as <foreign xml:lang="la">ergo</foreign> are usually removed. The cumulative effect of these changes is to transform Hugh’s work into a more efficient and direct treatise that could be quickly internalized. The annotations to Mazarine 717 indicate that readers found Hugh’s text difficult to navigate for reference purposes, and a could memorize Samuel’s verses to remember the system, and use the book when necessary to find the most useful passages.</p>
                    <p>In many ways, <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> would be most helpful to someone who had already read Hugh’s text. Yet while it can be seen from the list of Samuel’s works, that he is normally careful to cite the sources he uses, <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> is an exception: he does not give any indication that it is copied from another source. This is typical of the intellectual culture of the Middle Ages, in which there was immense freedom to adapt the writings of others. This sometimes leaves today’s readers, unfamiliar with the writings of the period, with the concern that medieval writers intended to pass off the work of others as original. It might be argued that Samuel’s audience would have been so familiar with the work that they would recognize the source immediately. He might have had access to a copy of <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> at either Lincoln or Bury St Edmunds: three copies of the work survive in the library of Lincoln Cathedral, two from the twelfth century and one from the thirteenth;<ptr target="#note58" xml:id="nr58" n="58"/> Bury St Edmunds owned at least two copies, from the late twelfth and early thirteenth centuries.<ptr target="#note59" xml:id="nr59" n="59"/> In <title xml:lang="la">Ex diuersis auditis</title>, Samuel’s citations function to remind the reader of the authority of the texts he uses, and not to provide a location where the original might be found. He normally gives some form of attribution to biblical and classical sources, but the few references to works written within the preceding century are mostly integrated without comment. Hugh had been dead for little more than half a century when Samuel was writing, and his reputation was still rising. It was only the biblical sources that needed to be identified in order to communicate the subject at hand, and Samuel enhanced the citation of these over Hugh’s original.</p>
                    <p>Whereas many of Samuel’s other works were written in Leonines, which use an internal rhyming scheme, <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> is composed in unrhymed hexameter, usually but not always with a caesura in the third foot. The syntax is not complex. They are not particularly artful, but they are highly serviceable.</p>
                    <p>It is tempting to dismiss Samuel as a mere excerpter,<ptr target="#note60" xml:id="nr60" n="60"/> or as Brian Twyne thought, little more than a devotee of William de Montibus.<ptr target="#note61" xml:id="nr61" n="61"/> Samuel himself provides some idea of his motives behind his work. The opening folios of both Pembroke College, MS 115 and Oxford, Bodleian Library, MS Bodley 860 contain a text written as a <foreign xml:lang="la">distinctio</foreign> in red ink, forming hexameter lines that can be read in four different ways:</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="figures/pembroke-distinction-1r.jpg"/>
                        <head>Distinction in Cambridge, Pembroke College 115, fol. 1r.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <q xml:lang="la">
                        <l>Mens conseruetur per opus ne stulta uagetur.</l>
                        <l>Sic studiis detur ut que prosint operetur.</l>
                        <l>Mens conseruetur ut que prosint operetur.</l>
                        <l>Sic studiis detur per opus ne stulta uagetur.</l>
                    </q>
                    <q>
                        <l>The mind is maintained through work lest it roam in stupidity.</l>
                        <l>Thus it is given to study so that it may labour on useful things.</l>
                        <l>The mind is maintained that it may labour on useful things.</l>
                        <l>Thus it is given to study through work lest it roam in stupidity.</l>
                    </q>
                    <p>In the same format, both manuscripts have the following at the bottom of the last page of text (Bodley 860, fol. 206v; Pembroke College, MS 115, fol. 76r):</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="figures/pembroke-distinction-76r.jpg"/>
                        <head>Distinction in Cambridge, Pembroke College 115, fol. 76r.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <q xml:lang="la">
                        <l>Hec qui collegit eterna pace quiescat.</l>
                        <l>Hec quicumque legit oret simul ut requiescat.</l>
                        <l>Hec quicumque legit eterna pace quiescat.</l>
                        <l>Hec qui collegit oret simul ut requiescat.</l>
                    </q>
                    <q>
                        <l>May he who collected these things sleep in eternal peace.</l>
                        <l>May whoever reads these things pray likewise that he may rest.</l>
                        <l>May whoever reads these things sleep in eternal peace.</l>
                        <l>May he who collected these things pray likewise that he may rest.</l>
                    </q>
                    <p>These passages are highly characteristic of Samuel’s intellectual milieu. Their presence indicates that these two manuscripts were planned together in the form in which they have survived. These are collections of earlier units: Bodley 860 is a composite of three booklets, while Pembroke College 115 can be divided into two parts. Similar to the way in which Mazarine 717 represents a conscious effort to assemble the works of Hugh of St Victor, the Bury manuscripts are an attempt to provide Samuel’s writings in a presentable form, in this case with the author’s own involvement.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115</head>
                    <p>Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115<ptr target="#note62" xml:id="nr62" n="62"/> is written entirely on parchment in Latin, with pages measuring around 230 × 163 mm. A pressmark of <q>S. 2</q> on the upper flyleaf indicates its cataloguing in the abbey of Bury St Edmunds by the librarian Henry Kirkestede (ca. 1314–ca. 1378). This categorizes it with material that might have been used for preaching: S. 1 was a copy of Sallust, S. 18 Suetonius, and many of the later volumes were sermon collections.<ptr target="#note63" xml:id="nr63" n="63"/> Its sibling, now Bodley 860, was B. 233, placing it with commentaries on the Psalms. The manuscripts were among others from Bury bequeathed to Pembroke College by William Smart in 1599,<ptr target="#note64" xml:id="nr64" n="64"/> Bodley 860 being one of thirty-one manuscripts separated from the Pembroke collection.<ptr target="#note65" xml:id="nr65" n="65"/></p>
                    <p>The volume is collated 1<hi rend="sup">8</hi>–5<hi rend="sup">8</hi>, 6<hi rend="sup">8–2</hi> (7/8 cancelled) || 7<hi rend="sup">8</hi>–9<hi rend="sup">8</hi>, 10<hi rend="sup">8–1</hi> (8 cancelled). The cancelled leaves between fols. 46 and 47 would presumably have been blank, as is fol. 46v: the contents are uninterrupted. The second booklet corresponds to <title xml:lang="la">Collecta ex speculo beati Gregorii sine uersibus</title>, which has different ruling (in plummet rather than pencil) and a simpler scheme of decorated capitals from the rest of the volume. The same fashion of the final booklet of Bodley 860, the order of the internal pages of most gatherings are designated by letters, and a number (·i· through ·ix·) is found at the end of each gathering at the bottom of the page, in the centre, written in ink.</p>
                    <p>While the page layout is visually similar to Bodley 860, the ruling pattern differs slightly. In the Pembroke manuscript, the line spacing is variable, generally leaving 4.5 mm for prose and 7 mm for verses. This appears to have been done before the page was copied, and where this was not correctly planned, either the verse has to span two lines or a 7 mm line is subdivided for two shorter lines of prose. This can be seen, for example, on fol. 6r. The lines of the prose passages in Bodley 860 are similarly 4.5 mm high, but two full lines (9 to 10 mm) are left for the verses, simplifying the page preparation process.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="figures/pembroke-ruling-6r.jpg"/>
                        <head>Variable ruling on Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115, fol. 6r.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>The evidence suggests that Samuel was involved personally in the production of Pembroke College 115 and Bodley 860, with a correcting hand found in both manuscripts. This corrector is intimately familiar with the text, and seems to have gone through it methodically after it was copied; he leaves a faint note in the lower corner of MS Bodley 860, fol. 103r that reads <q>usque hunc in parte</q>. Its contemporaneity is demonstrated by fol. 39r, where one also finds additional verses copied into the margin, in turn recopied by a contemporary scribe imitating the original hand. The correction has been trimmed in binding, and as the manuscript appears to be in its original medieval binding, this was probably done at the time of production. While this correction might have been caught by anyone working with the exemplar, the same hand also makes original revisions to the text. The corrector is also highly interested in detail, extensively revising the punctuation (often, for instance, changing a <foreign xml:lang="la">punctus</foreign> to a <foreign xml:lang="la">punctus eleuatus</foreign>). The most likely identity for this corrector is Samuel himself.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="figures/pembroke-correction-28r.jpg"/>
                        <head>Marginal correction to Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115, fol. 28r.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="figures/pembroke-correction-39r.jpg"/>
                        <head>Inline and marginal corrections to Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115, fol. 39r, with added verses later recopied at the bottom of the page by a contemporary scribe.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="figures/pembroke-correction-66r.jpg"/>
                        <head>Inline and marginal corrections to Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115, fol. 66r.</head>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Editing <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title></head>
                    <p>As Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115, fols. 41v–44v is the sole witness to <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title>, and it has never been previously edited, a documentary edition of this manuscript encapsules the full known history of this text. In this situation, one of the best things that an editor can do is to create an edition that can be cited in the same way as the manuscript. For instance, while Baron’s edition of Mazarine 717 cites the folio and column breaks (though a few are missing), the only possible method of referring to a more specific passage in Hugh’s text is to use the line numbers in Baron’s own edition. Some scholars have instead chosen to refer to the Patrologia Latina columns (not included in Baron edition) and use Migne’s text. By instead recording the position of line breaks in the manuscript, one can maintain the citation systems that already exist, and refrain from perpetuating a new scheme. This is, indeed, a necessity for the flexible layout of electronic texts, where stable references must refer either to a physical object or a semantic division.</p>
                    <p>One of the problems of <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> (like all of Samuel’s verse-prose compilations) is that its layout does not fit with a key modern assumption of how a book should work: one cannot start reading at the top of the page and scan to the bottom. Instead, the text begins with the commentary, which is pared with the applicable line of verse below it. The commentary is far longer than the verses, meaning that the individual verse of the poem must be searched out over the entire text. In a printed version of this text, an editor would be forced to choose between rearranging the text to promote readability, and bringing the reader to the original – maintaining the ability to cite the manuscript by folio, the possibility of making better historical inferences about how readers might have used the text, and the prospect of experiencing non-linear habits of reading. This is only possible by relying on semantic categories rather than typographical conventions to interpret the text (for example, explicitly marking a line as verse rather than simply displaying it in enlarged type), and displaying the text in both documentary and regular forms. This is a distinct advantage of presenting texts in a digital format.</p>
                    <p>The verses of <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> are entirely sensible as corrected, but the prose requires several emendations. The text is slightly different from that of Mazarine 717, including a few variants recorded by Baron, though not corresponding to any one of his manuscripts. Like most manuscripts of this period, capital letters are used only to indicate the beginning of a sentence, but one of the challenges of the particular script is an ambiguity between majuscule and minuscule characters. Some of the distinctions identified in the edition are judgements based on sense rather than visual appearance.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methodology: Aligning Editions with Research Questions</head>
                <p>After half a century of using computers in scholarly editing, classical and medieval historians have yet to agree on standards for what needs to be included in a digital edition. The focus tends to remain on adapting the standards of printed critical editions to a digital format, skipping the step of considering the specific technological restrictions and intellectual emphases that originally brought forth the peculiar format of the critical edition in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. If one examines this history, it quickly becomes apparent that applying the technological restrictions of the printing press is purely artificial, resulting in the complete lack of agreement as to how one should encode a critical apparatus in a digital format. Further, the vast number of important texts that still must be read in an early-modern edition shows the sheer impracticality of the recensionist ideal for editions, now exacerbated by an academic funding model that promotes short-term projects. There have long been calls for integrating codicology into editorial practices.<ptr target="#note66" xml:id="nr66" n="66"/> A solution can be found in the principles of documentary editing, and superseding the critical apparatus by developing better ways to provide historical context by comparing textual variants.</p>
                <p>The rationale for documentary editing in a digital context has already been stated,<ptr target="#note67" xml:id="nr67" n="67"/> but there are not yet established guidelines for applying this to medieval Latin literary texts. Digital editing provides the ability to record information in an edition that might be useful to answering certain research questions but might otherwise inhibit the reading of a text. Further, as shown in the case of <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title>, common and explicit terminology forces editors to be clearer about their interpretations rather than ask readers to infer meaning from devices of punctuation and layout that can be interpreted according to many different conventions.</p>
                <p>Yet this removal of the limitations of print also means that it is necessary to set new boundaries for oneself. Due to the incredible uniqueness of handwritten sources, there is no limit to the amount of information one can record about them, and there is correspondingly a vast number of tags available as part of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) that many editors will never need, but their presence raises the question of whether they are necessary. Editors are told that TEI guidelines should be applied in the way that best fits their research questions – but editors work for others as much as themselves. If one wishes to produce texts that can be reused by other researchers and fit within larger corpora, the potential scope of research questions applying to premodern texts needs to be coordinated with the scribal practices one must interpret in editing manuscripts. Without a corpus of digital texts for study to which one can add one’s work, and without any clear indication of how TEI elements can be analysed, it often happens that one only realizes during the process of editing that it would have been useful to have recorded a certain feature. The documentary editions of both Hugh’s and Samuel’s texts produced here are in part an experiment to determine what information can be practically and scientifically recorded from typical, relatively uncomplicated manuscripts, building off earlier studies of more complex phenomena.<ptr target="#note68" xml:id="nr68" n="68"/></p>
                <p>In determining what should be encoded in editions of works from this period, the possible levels of detail were narrowed down to four layers corresponding to likely uses for the texts:<ptr target="#note69" xml:id="nr69" n="69"/></p>
                <list type="ordered">
                    <item>Basic transcription necessary to read and search the text of the manuscript, and find significant variants in a collation with other witnesses. To meet this need, markup may be light, sometimes even the result of a text produced from an old edition via optical character recognition (OCR) software. Spelling can be normalized, as there should be no expectation at this level of using such texts for fine-grained linguistic research, and editors of critical editions do not normally consider such differences to be noteworthy.</item>
                    <item>Information required to cite manuscripts with precision and study minor variants between witnesses, including changes in spelling and punctuation. Any modifications to the manuscript should be indicated using the appropriate tags (e.g. <eg>&lt;add&gt;</eg>, <eg>&lt;corr&gt;</eg>). The edition should encode the position of line breaks (if only to facilitate verifying one’s work against the manuscript), and follow original spelling as far as abbreviations allow, though it may be necessary to silently regularize word division to some extent. Punctuation and capitalization should be regularized only if necessary; appropriate tags should be used for indicating quotation (e.g. <eg>&lt;quote&gt;</eg>, <eg>&lt;said&gt;</eg>, <eg>&lt;mentioned&gt;</eg>) rather than inserting quotation marks. As a matter of practicality, if one wishes to capitalize proper names in a reader’s version (until late in the Middle Ages, it was common to use capitals only for first letter of a sentence), it is easiest to accomplish this by marking the words with <eg>&lt;name&gt;</eg>, <eg>&lt;title&gt;</eg>, etc., which also allows the terms to be compiled in an index. Abbreviations may be silently expanded, though it may be helpful to record them in cases of ambiguity.</item>
                    <item>Information necessary to study the exact contemporary reading of the text and precise spelling, together with the scribe’s linguistic profile:<ptr target="#note70" xml:id="nr70" n="70"/> all of the above, mandating the preservation of the original punctuation, encoding editorial regularizations of hyphenation and word division, and documenting all expansions of abbreviations.</item>
                    <item>Information needed for statistical analysis of a scribe’s graphic profile:<ptr target="#note71" xml:id="nr71" n="71"/> the above in addition to full encoding of abbreviation markers and unusual letterforms relevant for palaeographical study (e.g. round and long <q>s</q>).</item>
                </list>
                <p>Most electronic editions available today would fall into the first category: they are still of far more use than nothing at all. Most new digital editions would probably fall into the second category: this is the point at which the most broadly useful features of the manuscript can recorded before the XML file starts to become too unwieldy to edit by hand. The third and fourth categories are more specialized, but represent real and useful research questions, and with better software these levels would become more easily achievable. It is much easier to upgrade a transcription from one level to another than to start afresh, and over time, scholars could build up one another’s work through all these stages based on the problems they need to solve.</p>
                <p>One could think of this approach in terms of restoring a building, or a work of art: when one edits a manuscript in a digital format, it is possible to carefully erect new walls without destroying the what is there, and years later it will still be possible for someone else to redecorate without cursing us for destroying the original fixtures. Rearranging a text for print is usually more akin to gutting a room and rebuilding it entirely to fit modern trends. At the same time, because one is creating a technology-independent edition that can have more than one possible layout rather than one tied precisely to the needs of paper, it is not necessary to sacrifice usability.</p>
                <p>The present editions of <title xml:lang="la">De quinque septenis</title> and <title xml:lang="la">De oratione dominica</title> fall into the third category above, with the aim of better understanding the punctuation and spelling of this period. Similar to the most recent edition of Hugh’s <title xml:lang="la">De sacramentis</title>,<ptr target="#note72" xml:id="nr72" n="72"/> these editions use the original punctuation from the manuscript. In order to track the spelling with precision, it was necessary to show precisely which letters were interpreted by the editor – a long-standing expectation for diplomatic editions of vernacular and some Latin texts. Words such as <foreign xml:lang="la">Christus</foreign> are never spelled out in full in the text; although there is evidence to suggest that <foreign xml:lang="la">Cristus</foreign> was the most common spelling in England of the thirteenth-century (and certainly in the Samuel Presbiter manuscripts), this is rarely found in editions. Transcribing a medieval manuscript with its abbreviations can also save time and increase accuracy in transcription: by using text-expansion software, one can type, for example, <q>.spc</q> and receive the TEI <eg rend="xml"><hi rend="kw">&lt;expan&gt;&lt;abbr</hi><hi rend="ot"> rend=</hi><hi rend="st">"supraline"</hi><hi rend="kw">&gt;</hi>sp&lt;am&gt;</hi>c<hi rend="kw">&lt;/am&gt;<hi rend="kw">&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;ex&gt;</hi>iritus<hi rend="kw">&lt;/ex&gt;&lt;/expan&gt;</hi></eg>. Ultimately, the methodology of digital documentary editing allows us to produce editions much more quickly and accurate, in form that can be straightforwardly verified and corrected, and applied to a much wider range of research.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="acknowledgements">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>Images of Cambridge, Pembroke College, MS 115, taken by the author in November 2013, are reproduced here by permission of the Master and Fellows of Pembroke College, Cambridge. Images of Paris, Bibliothèque Mazarine, MS 717 are reproduced courtesy of the Bibliothèque Mazarine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <p>Abbey of St Victor, Paris. <title>M. Hugonis de S. Victore, canonici regularis, sancti Victoris parisiensis, tum pietate, tum doctrina insignis; Opera omnia tribus tomis digesta</title>. 3 vols. Rouen: Berthelin, 1648.</p>
                <p>Adriaen, Marc, ed. <title>S. Gregorii Magni Moralia in Iob</title>. Corpus Christianorum, series latina 143, 143a, 143b. Turnhout: Brepols, 1979–1985.</p>
                <p>Baron, Roger. <q>Étude sur l’authenticité de l’œuvre de Hugues de Saint-Victor d’après les manuscrits Paris, B. Mazarine 717, BN 14506 et Douai 360–366.</q> <title>Scriptorium</title> 10, no. 2 (1956): 182–220. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.3406/scrip.1956.2703">10.3406/scrip.1956.2703</ref>.</p>
                <p>———. <title>Études sur Hugues de Saint-Victor</title>. Paris: de Brouwer, 1963.</p>
                <p>———, ed. <title>Hugues de Saint-Victor. Six opuscules spirituels</title>. Translated by Roger Baron. Sources chrétiennes 155. Paris: Cerf, 1969.</p>
                <p>———. <q>Hugues de Saint-Victor: Contribution à un nouvel examen de son œuvre.</q> <title>Traditio</title> 15 (1959): 223–97. <ref target="http://jstor.org/stable/27830387">http://jstor.org/stable/27830387</ref>.</p>
                <p>Bernard, Edward. <title>Catalogi librorum manuscriptorum Angliæ et Hiberniæ in unum collecti</title>. 2 vols. Oxford: Sheldonian Theatre, 1697.</p>
                <p>Berndt, Rainer, ed. <title>Hugonis de Sancto Victore De sacramentis Christiane fidei</title>. Corpus Victorinum, Textus historici 1. Münster: Aschendorff, 2008.</p>
                <p>———. <q>The Writings of Hugh of St Victor: An Author and His Contexts.</q> In <title>Ugo di San Vittore: Atti del XLVII Convegno storico internazionale, Todi, 10–12 ottobre 2010</title>, 1–20. Atti dei Convegni del Centro italiano di studi sul basso Medioevo, Accademia Tudertina, n.s., 24. Spoleto: Fondazione Centro italiano di studi sull’alto Medioevo, 2011.</p>
                <p>Bloomfield, Morton W., Bertrand-Georges Guyot, Donald R. Howard, and Thyra B. Kabealo. <title>Incipits of Latin Works on the Virtues and Vices, 1100–1500 A.D.: Including a Section of Incipits of Works on the Pater Noster</title>. Mediaeval Academy of America Publication 88. Cambridge, MA: Mediaeval Academy of America, 1979. <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.31131.0001.001">http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.31131.0001.001</ref>.</p>
                <p>Boyle, Leonard E. <q>Optimist and Recensionist: <q>Common Errors</q> or <q>Common Variations</q>?</q> In <title>Latin Script and Letters, AD 400–900: Festschrift Presented to Ludwig Bieler on the Occasion of His 70th Birthday</title>, edited by John J. O’Meara and Bernd Naumann, 264–74. Leiden: Brill, 1976.</p>
                <p>———. <q>The Inter-Conciliar Period 1179–1215 and the Beginnings of Pastoral Manuals.</q> In <title>Miscellanea Rolando Bandinelli, Papa Alessandro III</title>, edited by Filippo Liotta, 45–56. Siena: Accademia senese degli intronati, 1986.</p>
                <p>Buttimer, Charles Henry. <title>Hugonis de Sancto Victore Didascalicon de studio legendi: A Critical Text</title>. Washington, DC: Catholic University Press, 1939.</p>
                <p>Caillau, Armand-Benjamin, and Benjamin Saint-Yves, eds. <title>Sancti Aurelii Augustini Hipponensis episcopi Operum supplementum I. Continens Sermones ineditos extractos ex Archivio Montis-Cassini et ex Bibliotheca Laurentiana-Medicea Florentiæ</title>. Paris: Parent-Desbarres, 1836.</p>
                <p>Carruthers, Mary J. <title>The Book of Memory: A Study of Memory in Medieval Culture</title>. 2nd ed. Cambridge Studies in Medieval Literature 10. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2008. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781107051126">10.1017/CBO9781107051126</ref>.</p>
                <p>Clichtove, Josse, and Pierre de Porta, eds. <title>In hoc libro contenta opera Hugonis de Sancto Victore. De institutione novitiorum. De operibus trium dierum. De arra anime. De laude charitatis. De modo orandi. Duplex exposito orationis dominice. De quinque septenis. De septem donis Spiritus Sancti</title>. Paris: Stephanus, 1506. <ref target="http://lib.ugent.be/catalog/bkt01:000321097">http://lib.ugent.be/catalog/bkt01:000321097</ref>.</p>
                <p>Coolman, Boyd Taylor. <q>Hugh of St. Victor.</q> In <title>The Sermon on the Mount Through the Centuries</title>, edited by Jeffrey P. Greenman, Timothy Larsen, and Stephen R. Spencer, 59–80. Grand Rapids, MI: Brazos Press, 2007.</p>
                <p>———. <title>The Theology of Hugh of St. Victor: An Interpretation</title>. New York: Cambridge University Press, 2010.</p>
                <p>de Ghellinck, Joseph. <q>La table des matières de la première édition des œuvres de Hugues de Saint-Victor.</q> <title>Recherches de science religieuse</title> 1 (1910): 270–89, 385–96.</p>
                <p>Deferrari, Roy J., trans. <title>On the Sacraments of the Christian Faith (De sacramentis)</title>. Mediaeval Academy of America Publication 58. Cambridge, MA: Mediaeval Academy of America, 1951.</p>
                <p>Diem, Albrecht. <q>Virtues and Vices in Early Texts on Pastoral Care.</q> <title>Franciscan Studies</title> 62 (2004): 193–223. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/frc.2004.0008">10.1353/frc.2004.0008</ref>.</p>
                <p>Dinkova-Bruun, Greti. <q>Biblical Versifications from Late Antiquity to the Middle of the Thirteenth Century: History or Allegory?</q> In <title>Poetry and Exegesis in Premodern Latin Christianity: The Encounter Between Classical and Christian Strategies of Interpretation</title>, edited by Willemien Otten and Karla Pollmann, 315–42. Supplements to <title>Vigiliae Christianae</title> 87. Leiden: Brill, 2007. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1163/ej.9789004160699.i-364.65">10.1163/ej.9789004160699.i-364.65</ref>.</p>
                <p>———. <q>Samuel Presbyter and the Glosses to His Versification of Psalm 1: An Anti-Church Invective?</q> In <title>Florilegium mediaevale: Études offertes à Jacqueline Hamesse à l’occasion de son éméritat</title>, edited by José Francisco Meirinhos and Olga Weijers, 155–74. Textes et études du moyen âge 50. Louvain-la-Neuve: Fédération Internationale des Instituts d’Études Médiévales, 2009.</p>
                <p>Dunning, Andrew, ed. <title>Samuel Presbiter, Notes from the School of William de Montibus: Collecta ex diuersis auditis in scola magistri Willelmi de Monte</title>. Toronto Medieval Latin Texts 33. Toronto: Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies, 2015.</p>
                <p>Edstam, Torsten Kitada. <q>From Twelfth-Century Renaissance to Fifteenth-Century Reform: The Reception of Hugh of St. Victor in the Later Middle Ages.</q> PhD diss., University of Chicago, 2014. <ref target="http://search.proquest.com/docview/1615129493">http://search.proquest.com/docview/1615129493</ref>.</p>
                <p>Foster, C.W., and Kathleen Major, eds. <title>The Registrum Antiquissimum of the Cathedral Church of Lincoln</title>. 10 vols. Publications of the Lincoln Record Society 27–29, 32, 34, 41, 42, 46, 51, 62, 67, 68. Hereford: Lincoln Record Society, 1931–1968.</p>
                <p>Giraud, Cédric, and Patricia Stirnemann. <q>Le rayonnement de l’école de Saint-Victor: Manuscrits de la Bibliothèque Mazarine.</q> In <title>L’école de Saint-Victor de Paris: Influence et rayonnement du Moyen Âge à l’époque moderne</title>, edited by Dominique Poirel, 653–66. Bibliotheca Victorina 22. Turnhout: Brepols, 2010. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1484/M.BV-EB.3.4430">10.1484/M.BV-EB.3.4430</ref>.</p>
                <p>Gobbitt, Thomas. <q>Orthographic Preferences in the Production of Cambridge, Corpus Christi College MS 383 at the Turn of the Twelfth Century.</q> <title>Scriptorium</title> 66 (2012): 3–24.</p>
                <p>Goering, Joseph W. <title>William de Montibus (c. 1140–1213): The Schools and the Literature of Pastoral Care</title>. Studies and Texts 108. Toronto: Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies, 1992.</p>
                <p>Goy, Rudolf. <title>Die Überlieferung der Werke Hugos von St. Viktor: Ein Beitrag zur Kommunikationsgeschichte des Mittelalters</title>. Monographien zur Geschichte des Mittelalters 14. Stuttgart: Hiersemann, 1976.</p>
                <p>Gransden, Antonia. <title>A History of the Abbey of Bury St Edmunds, 1182–1256: Samson of Tottington to Edmund of Walpole</title>. Studies in the History of Medieval Religion 31. Woodbridge, Suffolk: Boydell Press, 2007.</p>
                <p>Green, William M. <q>Hugo of St. Victor: <title>De tribus maximis circumstantiis gestorum</title>.</q> <title>Speculum</title> 18, no. 4 (October 1943): 484–93. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2853664">10.2307/2853664</ref>.</p>
                <p>Hauréau, Barthélemy. <title>Les œuvres de Hugues de Saint-Victor: Essai critique</title>. Paris: Hachette, 1886. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/lesoeuvresdehugu00haur">https://archive.org/details/lesoeuvresdehugu00haur</ref>.</p>
                <p>Hugo de Sancto Victore. <title>Didascalicon de studio legendi et alia opuscula</title>. Strasbourg, 1474. <ref target="https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:hbz:061:1-68066">https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:hbz:061:1-68066</ref>.</p>
                <p>Hunt, R.W., Falconer Madan, and P.D. Record. <title>A Summary Catalogue of Western Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title>. 7 in 8 vols. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1895–1953.</p>
                <p>Inguanez, Maurus. <title>Codicum casinensium manuscriptorum catalogus</title>. 3 vols. Monte Cassino, 1915–1941.</p>
                <p>James, M.R. <q>Bury St. Edmunds Manuscripts.</q> <title>English Historical Review</title> 41, no. 162 (April 1926): 251–60. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ehr/XLI.CLXII.251">10.1093/ehr/XLI.CLXII.251</ref>.</p>
                <p>———. <title>On the Abbey of S. Edmund at Bury</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge Antiquarian Society, 1895. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/abbeyofsedmundat00jame">https://archive.org/details/abbeyofsedmundat00jame</ref>.</p>
                <p>James, M.R., and Ellis H. Minns. <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Pembroke College, Cambridge, with a Hand List of the Printed Books to the Year 1500</title>. Cambridge: University Press, 1905. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511692796">10.1017/CBO9780511692796</ref>.</p>
                <p>James, Thomas. <title>Ecloga Oxonio-Cantabrigiensis</title>. 2 vols. London: Bishop and Norton, 1600.</p>
                <p>Knauer, Peter S., trans. <title>Hugo von Sankt Viktor. Über die Heiltümer des christlichen Glaubens</title>. Corpus Victorinum, Schriften 1. Münster: Aschendorff, 2010.</p>
                <p>Lemoine, Michel, trans. <title>Hugues de Saint-Victor. L’art de lire/Didascalicon</title>. Paris: Cerf, 1991.</p>
                <p>Lottin, Odon. <q>La doctrine d’Anselme de Laon sur les dons du Saint-Esprit et son influence.</q> <title>Recherches de théologie ancienne et médiévale</title> 24 (1957): 267–95.</p>
                <p>Migne, Jacques Paul, ed. <title>Hugonis de S. Victore, canonici regularis, Sancti Victoris Parisiensis, tum pietate, tum doctrina insignis, Opera omnia tribus tomis digesta</title>. 3 vols. Patrologia Latina 175–177. Paris: Migne, 1854.</p>
                <p>Mutzenbecher, Almut, ed. <title>Sancti Aurelii Augustini De sermone domini in monte libros duos</title>. Corpus Christianorum, series latina 35. Turnhout: Brepols, 1967.</p>
                <p>Newhauser, Richard. <q>The Capital Vices as Medieval Anthropology.</q> In <title>Laster im Mittelalter/Vices in the Middle Ages</title>, edited by Christoph Flüeler and Martin Rohde, 105–24. Scrinium Friburgense 23. Berlin: De Gruyter, 2009. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110217377.105">10.1515/9783110217377.105</ref>.</p>
                <p>———. <title>The Treatise on Vices and Virtues in Latin and the Vernacular</title>. Typologie des sources du Moyen Age occidental 68. Turnhout: Brepols, 1993.</p>
                <p>Newhauser, Richard, and István Bejczy. <title>A Supplement to Morton W. Bloomfield et al., <title>Incipits of Latin Works on the Virtues and Vices, 1100–1500 A.D.</title></title> Instrumenta Patristica et Mediaevalia 50. Turnhout: Brepols, 2008.</p>
                <p>Offergeld, Thilo, trans. <title>Hugo von Sankt Viktor. Didascalicon de studio legendi/Studienbuch</title>. Fontes Christiani 27. Freiburg: Herder, 1997.</p>
                <p>Ouy, Gilbert. <title>Les manuscrits de l’Abbaye de Saint-Victor: catalogue établi sur la base du répertoire de Claude de Grandrue (1514)</title>. 2 vols. Bibliotheca Victorina 10. Turnhout: Brepols, 1999.</p>
                <p>Parkes, M.B. <q>Latin Autograph Manuscripts: Orthography and Punctuation.</q> In <title>Gli autografi medievali: Problemi paleografici e filologici. Atti del convegno di studio della Fondazione Ezio Franceschini, Erice, 25 settembre–2 ottobre 1990</title>, edited by Paolo Chiesa and Lucia Pinelli, 23–36. Quaderni di cultura mediolatina 5. Spoleto: Centro italiano di studi sull’alto Medioevo, 1994.</p>
                <p>Pierazzo, Elena. <q>A Rationale of Digital Documentary Editions.</q> <title>Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 26, no. 4 (December 2011): 463–77. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqr033">10.1093/llc/fqr033</ref>.</p>
                <p>———. <q>Digital Documentary Editions and the Others.</q> <title>Scholarly Editing</title> 35 (2014). <ref target="http://scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html">http://scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html</ref>.</p>
                <p>Pierazzo, Elena, and Peter A. Stokes. <q>Putting the Text back into Context: A Codicological Approach to Manuscript Transcription.</q> In <title>Kodikologie und Paläographie im digitalen Zeitalter/Codicology and Palaeography in the Digital Age</title>, edited by Franz Fischer, Christiane Fritze, and Georg Vogeler, 2:397–429. Schriften des Instituts für Dokumentologie und Editorik 3. Norderstedt: BoD, 2011. <ref target="https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:hbz:38-43605">https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:hbz:38-43605</ref>.</p>
                <p>Pipe Roll Society, ed. <title>Feet of Fines of the Tenth Year of the Reign of King Richard I, AD 1198 to AD 1199</title>. Publications of the Pipe Roll Society 24. London: Love and Wyman, 1900. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/piperollsociety24pipeuoft">https://archive.org/details/piperollsociety24pipeuoft</ref>.</p>
                <p>Poirel, Dominique. <q><title>Hugo Saxo</title>. Les origines germaniques de la pensée d’Hugues de Saint-Victor.</q> <title>Francia</title> 33, no. 1 (2006): 163–74. <ref target="http://francia.digitale-sammlungen.de/Blatt_bsb00016419,00193.html">http://francia.digitale-sammlungen.de/Blatt_bsb00016419,00193.html</ref>.</p>
                <p>———. <title>Livre de la nature et débat trinitaire au XIIe siècle: Le <title>De tribus diebus</title> de Hugues de Saint-Victor</title>. Bibliotheca Victorina 14. Turnhout: Brepols, 2002.</p>
                <p><title>Primo hoc Tomo Operum M. Hugonis a S. Victore contenta Epistola nuncupatoria et epigrammata, Opera tribus tomis hactenus impressa, Loca bibliorum sacrorrum ab Hugone exposita, deinde primi tomi tabula et post erratula</title>. Paris: Jodocus Badius and Johannes Parvus, 1526. <ref target="http://bibliotecavirtual.larioja.org/bvrioja/i18n/consulta/registro.cmd?id=1026">http://bibliotecavirtual.larioja.org/bvrioja/i18n/consulta/registro.cmd?id=1026</ref>.</p>
                <p>Quantin, Jean-Louis. <q>La réception d’Hugues et Richard de Saint-Victor au miroir de leurs <title>Opera omnia</title> (XVIe–XVIIe siècles).</q> In <title>L’école de Saint-Victor de Paris: Influence et rayonnement du Moyen Âge à l’époque moderne</title>, edited by Dominique Poirel, 601–42. Bibliotheca Victorina 22. Turnhout: Brepols, 2010. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1484/M.BV-EB.3.4428">10.1484/M.BV-EB.3.4428</ref>.</p>
                <p>Rehm, Ulrich. <title>Bebilderte Vaterunser-Erklärungen des Mittelalters</title>. Saecula spiritalia 28. Baden-Baden: Koerner, 1994.</p>
                <p>Rorem, Paul. <title>Hugh of Saint Victor</title>. Great Medieval Thinkers. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2009. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780195384369.001.0001">10.1093/acprof:oso/9780195384369.001.0001</ref>.</p>
                <p>Rudolph, Conrad. <title>The Mystic Ark: Hugh of Saint Victor, Art, and Thought in the Twelfth Century</title>. New York: Cambridge University Press, 2014. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781139583459">10.1017/CBO9781139583459</ref>.</p>
                <p>Russell, Josiah Cox. <title>Dictionary of Writers of Thirteenth-Century England</title>. Bulletin of the Institute of Historical Research, Special Supplement 3. London: Longmans, 1936.</p>
                <p>Sannelli, Massimo, trans. <title>Ugo di San Vittore, Didascalicon. De studio legendi/Dell’arte di leggere</title>. Lavis: La finestra, 2011.</p>
                <p>Sharpe, Richard. <q>Reconstructing the Medieval Library of Bury St Edmunds Abbey: The Lost Catalogue of Henry of Kirkstead.</q> In <title>Bury St Edmunds: Medieval Art, Architecture, Archaeology, and Economy</title>, edited by Antonia Gransden, 204–18. Conference Transactions 20. Leeds: British Archaeological Association, 1998.</p>
                <p>Sharpe, Richard, James P. Carley, Rodney M. Thomson, and Andrew G. Watson, eds. <title>English Benedictine Libraries: The Shorter Catalogues</title>. Corpus of British Medieval Library Catalogues 4. London: British Library, 1996.</p>
                <p>Sicard, Patrice. <title>Diagrammes médiévaux et exégèse visuelle: Le <title>Libellus de formatione arche</title> de Hugues de Saint-Victor</title>. Bibliotheca Victorina 4. Turnhout: Brepols, 1993.</p>
                <p>———, ed. <title>Hugonis de Sancto Victore De archa Noe. Libellus de formatione arche</title>. Corpus Christianorum, continuatio mediaevalis 176. Turnhout: Brepols, 2001.</p>
                <p>Stammberger, Ralf M.W. <q>Die Edition der Werke Hugos von Sankt Viktor († 1141) durch Abt Gilduin von Sankt Viktor († 1155) – Eine Rekonstruktion.</q> In <title>Schrift, Schreiber, Schenker: Studien zur Abtei Sankt Viktor in Paris und den Viktorinern</title>, edited by Rainer Berndt. Corpus Victorinum, Instrumenta 1. Berlin: Akademie Verlag, 2005.</p>
                <p>Stirnemann, Patricia. <q>Où ont été fabriqués les livres de la glose ordinaire dans la première moitié du XIIe siècle?</q> In <title>Le XIIe siècle: Mutations et renouveau en France dans la première moitié du XIIe siècle</title>, edited by Françoise Gasparri, 257–301. Cahiers du Léopard d’or 3. Paris: Léopard d’or, 1994.</p>
                <p>Sweeney, Eileen C. <q>Aquinas on the Seven Deadly Sins: Tradition and Innovation.</q> In <title>Sin in Medieval and Early Modern Culture: The Tradition of the Seven Deadly Sins</title>, edited by Richard Newhauser and Susan J. Ridyard, 85–106. Woodbridge, Suffolk: York Medieval Press, 2012.</p>
                <p>Tanner, Thomas. <title>Bibliotheca Britannico-Hibernica, siue, De scriptoribus, qui in Anglia, Scotia, et Hibernia ad saeculi XVII initium floruerunt, commentarius</title>. Edited by David Wilkins. London: Bowyer, 1748.</p>
                <p>Taylor, Barry. <q>Past, Present and Future for Thirteenth-Century Wales: Two Diagrams in British Library, Cotton Roll XIV.12.</q> <title>Electronic British Library Journal</title>, 2013. <ref target="http://bl.uk/eblj/2013articles/article13.html">http://bl.uk/eblj/2013articles/article13.html</ref>.</p>
                <p>Taylor, Jerome, trans. <title>The Didascalicon of Hugh of St. Victor: A Medieval Guide to the Arts</title>. Records of Civilization, Sources and Studies 64. New York: Columbia University Press, 1961. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/didascaliconmedi00hugh">https://archive.org/details/didascaliconmedi00hugh</ref>.</p>
                <p>Thomson, Rodney M. <title>Catalogue of the Manuscripts of Lincoln Cathedral Chapter Library</title>. Woodbridge, Suffolk: Brewer, 1989.</p>
                <p>Valgimogli, Lorenzo. <title>Lo <title xml:lang="la">Speculum Gregorii</title> di Adalberto di Metz</title>. Archivum Gregorianum 8. Florence: SISMEL, 2006.</p>
                <p>van den Eynde, Damien. <title>Essai sur la succession et la date des écrits de Hugues de Saint-Victor</title>. Spicilegium Pontificii Athenaei Antoniani 13. Rome: Pontificium Athenaeum Antonianum, 1960.</p>
                <p>Weber, Robert, Bonifatius Fischer, Jean Gribomont, Hedley F.D. Sparks, Walter Thiele, and Roger Gryson, eds. <title>Biblia Sacra iuxta vulgatam versionem</title>. 5th ed. Stuttgart: Deutsche Bibelgesellschaft, 2007.</p>
                <p>Wenzel, Siegfried. <q>The Seven Deadly Sins: Some Problems of Research.</q> <title>Speculum</title> 43, no. 1 (January 1968): 1–22. doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2854796">10.2307/2854796</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="notes">
                <note xml:id="note1">All biblical references follow Robert Weber et al., eds., <title>Biblia Sacra iuxta vulgatam versionem</title>, 5th ed. (Stuttgart: Deutsche Bibelgesellschaft, 2007): note that the beatitudes occur in a slightly different order from most English Bibles, and the Septuagint/Vulgate numeration of the Psalms differs from that of the Hebrew.</note>
                <note xml:id="note2">One hundred manuscripts are listed in Rudolf Goy, <title>Die Überlieferung der Werke Hugos von St. Viktor: Ein Beitrag zur Kommunikationsgeschichte des Mittelalters</title>, Monographien zur Geschichte des Mittelalters 14 (Stuttgart: Hiersemann, 1976), 368–83; see also Morton W. Bloomfield et al., <title>Incipits of Latin Works on the Virtues and Vices, 1100–1500 A.D.: Including a Section of Incipits of Works on the Pater Noster</title>, Mediaeval Academy of America Publication 88 (Cambridge, MA: Mediaeval Academy of America, 1979), 407–8 (no. 4833), <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.31131.0001.001">http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.31131.0001.001</ref>; Richard Newhauser and István Bejczy, <title>A Supplement to Morton W. Bloomfield et al., <title>Incipits of Latin Works on the Virtues and Vices, 1100–1500 A.D.</title></title>, Instrumenta Patristica et Mediaevalia 50 (Turnhout: Brepols, 2008), 275.</note>
                <note xml:id="note3">For a summary of Hugh’s ambiguous origins, see Paul Rorem, <title>Hugh of Saint Victor</title>, Great Medieval Thinkers (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2009), 9–11, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780195384369.001.0001">10.1093/acprof:oso/9780195384369.001.0001</ref>; Dominique Poirel, <q><title>Hugo Saxo</title>. Les origines germaniques de la pensée d’Hugues de Saint-Victor,</q> <title>Francia</title> 33, no. 1 (2006): 163–74, <ref target="http://francia.digitale-sammlungen.de/Blatt_bsb00016419,00193.html">http://francia.digitale-sammlungen.de/Blatt_bsb00016419,00193.html</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note4">Charles Henry Buttimer, <title>Hugonis de Sancto Victore Didascalicon de studio legendi: A Critical Text</title> (Washington, DC: Catholic University Press, 1939); English: Jerome Taylor, trans., <title>The Didascalicon of Hugh of St. Victor: A Medieval Guide to the Arts</title>, Records of Civilization, Sources and Studies 64 (New York: Columbia University Press, 1961), <ref target="https://archive.org/details/didascaliconmedi00hugh">https://archive.org/details/didascaliconmedi00hugh</ref>; French: Michel Lemoine, trans., <title>Hugues de Saint-Victor. L’art de lire/Didascalicon</title> (Paris: Cerf, 1991); German: Thilo Offergeld, trans., <title>Hugo von Sankt Viktor. Didascalicon de studio legendi/Studienbuch</title>, Fontes Christiani 27 (Freiburg: Herder, 1997); Italian: Massimo Sannelli, trans., <title>Ugo di San Vittore, Didascalicon. De studio legendi/Dell’arte di leggere</title> (Lavis: La finestra, 2011).</note>
                <note xml:id="note5">Rainer Berndt, ed., <title>Hugonis de Sancto Victore De sacramentis Christiane fidei</title>, Corpus Victorinum, Textus historici 1 (Münster: Aschendorff, 2008); English: Roy J. Deferrari, trans., <title>On the Sacraments of the Christian Faith (De sacramentis)</title>, Mediaeval Academy of America Publication 58 (Cambridge, MA: Mediaeval Academy of America, 1951); German: Peter S. Knauer, trans., <title>Hugo von Sankt Viktor. Über die Heiltümer des christlichen Glaubens</title>, Corpus Victorinum, Schriften 1 (Münster: Aschendorff, 2010).</note>
                <note xml:id="note6">Conrad Rudolph, <title>The Mystic Ark: Hugh of Saint Victor, Art, and Thought in the Twelfth Century</title> (New York: Cambridge University Press, 2014), doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781139583459">10.1017/CBO9781139583459</ref>; Patrice Sicard, ed., <title>Hugonis de Sancto Victore De archa Noe. Libellus de formatione arche</title>, Corpus Christianorum, continuatio mediaevalis 176 (Turnhout: Brepols, 2001); Patrice Sicard, <title>Diagrammes médiévaux et exégèse visuelle: Le <title>Libellus de formatione arche</title> de Hugues de Saint-Victor</title>, Bibliotheca Victorina 4 (Turnhout: Brepols, 1993).</note>
                <note xml:id="note7">Recent scholarship on this is summarized in Rainer Berndt, <q>The Writings of Hugh of St Victor: An Author and His Contexts,</q> in <title>Ugo di San Vittore: Atti del XLVII Convegno storico internazionale, Todi, 10–12 ottobre 2010</title>, Atti dei Convegni del Centro italiano di studi sul basso Medioevo, Accademia Tudertina, n.s., 24 (Spoleto: Fondazione Centro italiano di studi sull’alto Medioevo, 2011), 1–20.</note>
                <note xml:id="note8">Damien van den Eynde, <title>Essai sur la succession et la date des écrits de Hugues de Saint-Victor</title>, Spicilegium Pontificii Athenaei Antoniani 13 (Rome: Pontificium Athenaeum Antonianum, 1960), 215.</note>
                <note xml:id="note9">Roger Baron, <q>Hugues de Saint-Victor: Contribution à un nouvel examen de son œuvre,</q> <title>Traditio</title> 15 (1959): 276–78, <ref target="http://jstor.org/stable/27830387">http://jstor.org/stable/27830387</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note10">Summarized in more detail in Boyd Taylor Coolman, <title>The Theology of Hugh of St. Victor: An Interpretation</title> (New York: Cambridge University Press, 2010), 69–73; Boyd Taylor Coolman, <q>Hugh of St. Victor,</q> in <title>The Sermon on the Mount Through the Centuries</title>, ed. Jeffrey P. Greenman, Timothy Larsen, and Stephen R. Spencer (Grand Rapids, MI: Brazos Press, 2007), 59–80.</note>
                <note xml:id="note11">Richard Newhauser, <q>The Capital Vices as Medieval Anthropology,</q> in <title>Laster im Mittelalter/Vices in the Middle Ages</title>, ed. Christoph Flüeler and Martin Rohde, Scrinium Friburgense 23 (Berlin: De Gruyter, 2009), 105–24, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110217377.105">10.1515/9783110217377.105</ref>; Richard Newhauser, <title>The Treatise on Vices and Virtues in Latin and the Vernacular</title>, Typologie des sources du Moyen Age occidental 68 (Turnhout: Brepols, 1993), 180–202.</note>
                <note xml:id="note12"><title>Moralia in Iob</title> 31.45: Marc Adriaen, ed., <title>S. Gregorii Magni Moralia in Iob</title>, Corpus Christianorum, series latina 143, 143a, 143b (Turnhout: Brepols, 1979–1985), 143b:1610–13; Siegfried Wenzel, <q>The Seven Deadly Sins: Some Problems of Research,</q> <title>Speculum</title> 43, no. 1 (January 1968): 4, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2854796">10.2307/2854796</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note13">E.g. <title xml:lang="la">De sacramentis</title> 2.13.1: Berndt, <title>Hugonis de Sancto Victore De sacramentis Christiane fidei</title>, 481–83; <title>Scala celi</title>, edited in Roger Baron, <title>Études sur Hugues de Saint-Victor</title> (Paris: de Brouwer, 1963), 219–55.</note>
                <note xml:id="note14">For a comparison of Hugh’s categories with Augustine, Paschasius Radbertus, and Gregory the Great, see Ulrich Rehm, <title>Bebilderte Vaterunser-Erklärungen des Mittelalters</title>, Saecula spiritalia 28 (Baden-Baden: Koerner, 1994), 7–14.</note>
                <note xml:id="note15"><title>De sermo domini in monte</title> 1.10: Almut Mutzenbecher, ed., <title>Sancti Aurelii Augustini De sermone domini in monte libros duos</title>, Corpus Christianorum, series latina 35 (Turnhout: Brepols, 1967), 7–9.</note>
                <note xml:id="note16"><title>De sermo domini in monte</title> 1.11–12: Mutzenbecher, <title>Augustini De sermone domini in monte</title>, 9–13.</note>
                <note xml:id="note17"><title>De sermo domini in monte</title> 2.38: Mutzenbecher, <title>Augustini De sermone domini in monte</title>, 128–30.</note>
                <note xml:id="note18">Odon Lottin, <q>La doctrine d’Anselme de Laon sur les dons du Saint-Esprit et son influence,</q> <title>Recherches de théologie ancienne et médiévale</title> 24 (1957): 290–91.</note>
                <note xml:id="note19">Gilbert Ouy, <title>Les manuscrits de l’Abbaye de Saint-Victor: catalogue établi sur la base du répertoire de Claude de Grandrue (1514)</title>, Bibliotheca Victorina 10 (Turnhout: Brepols, 1999), 2:198 (CC 2).</note>
                <note xml:id="note20">Barthélemy Hauréau, <title>Les œuvres de Hugues de Saint-Victor: Essai critique</title> (Paris: Hachette, 1886), 22, <ref target="https://archive.org/details/lesoeuvresdehugu00haur">https://archive.org/details/lesoeuvresdehugu00haur</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note21">William M. Green, <q>Hugo of St. Victor: <title>De tribus maximis circumstantiis gestorum</title>,</q> <title>Speculum</title> 18, no. 4 (October 1943): 484–93, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2853664">10.2307/2853664</ref>; translated in Mary J. Carruthers, <title>The Book of Memory: A Study of Memory in Medieval Culture</title>, 2nd ed., Cambridge Studies in Medieval Literature 10 (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2008), 339–44, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781107051126">10.1017/CBO9781107051126</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note22">See Leonard E. Boyle, <q>The Inter-Conciliar Period 1179–1215 and the Beginnings of Pastoral Manuals,</q> in <title>Miscellanea Rolando Bandinelli, Papa Alessandro III</title>, ed. Filippo Liotta (Siena: Accademia senese degli intronati, 1986), 45–56; Albrecht Diem, <q>Virtues and Vices in Early Texts on Pastoral Care,</q> <title>Franciscan Studies</title> 62 (2004): 193–223, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/frc.2004.0008">10.1353/frc.2004.0008</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note23">Rehm, <title>Bebilderte Vaterunser-Erklärungen</title>, 20–26, 72–77.</note>
                <note xml:id="note24">Barry Taylor, <q>Past, Present and Future for Thirteenth-Century Wales: Two Diagrams in British Library, Cotton Roll XIV.12,</q> <title>Electronic British Library Journal</title>, 2013, 8–16, <ref target="http://bl.uk/eblj/2013articles/article13.html">http://bl.uk/eblj/2013articles/article13.html</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note25">Eileen C. Sweeney, <q>Aquinas on the Seven Deadly Sins: Tradition and Innovation,</q> in <title>Sin in Medieval and Early Modern Culture: The Tradition of the Seven Deadly Sins</title>, ed. Richard Newhauser and Susan J. Ridyard (Woodbridge, Suffolk: York Medieval Press, 2012), 99–101.</note>
                <note xml:id="note26">Rehm, <title>Bebilderte Vaterunser-Erklärungen</title>, 19–21; Torsten Kitada Edstam, <q>From Twelfth-Century Renaissance to Fifteenth-Century Reform: The Reception of Hugh of St. Victor in the Later Middle Ages</q> (PhD diss., University of Chicago, 2014), 198–207, <ref target="http://search.proquest.com/docview/1615129493">http://search.proquest.com/docview/1615129493</ref>; Newhauser, <q>The Capital Vices as Medieval Anthropology,</q> 118.</note>
                <note xml:id="note27">See Ralf M.W. Stammberger, <q>Die Edition der Werke Hugos von Sankt Viktor († 1141) durch Abt Gilduin von Sankt Viktor († 1155) – Eine Rekonstruktion,</q> in <title>Schrift, Schreiber, Schenker: Studien zur Abtei Sankt Viktor in Paris und den Viktorinern</title>, ed. Rainer Berndt, Corpus Victorinum, Instrumenta 1 (Berlin: Akademie Verlag, 2005); Dominique Poirel, <title>Livre de la nature et débat trinitaire au XIIe siècle: Le <title>De tribus diebus</title> de Hugues de Saint-Victor</title>, Bibliotheca Victorina 14 (Turnhout: Brepols, 2002), 27–86.</note>
                <note xml:id="note28">Joseph de Ghellinck, <q>La table des matières de la première édition des œuvres de Hugues de Saint-Victor,</q> <title>Recherches de science religieuse</title> 1 (1910): 280 (fol. 82r).</note>
                <note xml:id="note29">Rorem, <title>Hugh of Saint Victor</title>, 13–14.</note>
                <note xml:id="note30">Berndt, <title>Hugonis de Sancto Victore De sacramentis Christiane fidei</title>, 15.</note>
                <note xml:id="note31">Ouy, <title>Les manuscrits de l’Abbaye de Saint-Victor</title>, 2:256–57 (HH 1).</note>
                <note xml:id="note32">Roger Baron, <q>Étude sur l’authenticité de l’œuvre de Hugues de Saint-Victor d’après les manuscrits Paris, B. Mazarine 717, BN 14506 et Douai 360–366,</q> <title>Scriptorium</title> 10, no. 2 (1956): 189–90, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.3406/scrip.1956.2703">10.3406/scrip.1956.2703</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note33">Baron, <q>Étude sur l’authenticité de l’œuvre de Hugues de Saint-Victor d’après les manuscrits Paris, B. Mazarine 717, BN 14506 et Douai 360–366,</q> 183.</note>
                <note xml:id="note34">Patricia Stirnemann, <q>Où ont été fabriqués les livres de la glose ordinaire dans la première moitié du XIIe siècle?</q> in <title>Le XIIe siècle: Mutations et renouveau en France dans la première moitié du XIIe siècle</title>, ed. Françoise Gasparri, Cahiers du Léopard d’or 3 (Paris: Léopard d’or, 1994), 273, 284n64; Cédric Giraud and Patricia Stirnemann, <q>Le rayonnement de l’école de Saint-Victor: Manuscrits de la Bibliothèque Mazarine,</q> in <title>L’école de Saint-Victor de Paris: Influence et rayonnement du Moyen Âge à l’époque moderne</title>, ed. Dominique Poirel, Bibliotheca Victorina 22 (Turnhout: Brepols, 2010), 655, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1484/M.BV-EB.3.4430">10.1484/M.BV-EB.3.4430</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note35">Poirel, <title>Livre de la nature</title>, 37–49, with contents listed in appendix 1, 427–45.</note>
                <note xml:id="note36">Stammberger, <q>Die Edition der Werke Hugos von Sankt Viktor,</q> 123–36.</note>
                <note xml:id="note37">See the collation in Poirel, <title>Livre de la nature</title>, 40.</note>
                <note xml:id="note38">Hugo de Sancto Victore, <title>Didascalicon de studio legendi et alia opuscula</title> (Strasbourg, 1474), fols. 85r–88r of the final part of the volume, <q>Sententię vel assertiones Hugonis lucidissimę, in quibusdam verbis diuinis, et rerum naturis.</q>, <ref target="https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:hbz:061:1-68066">https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:hbz:061:1-68066</ref></note>
                <note xml:id="note39">Josse Clichtove and Pierre de Porta, eds., <title>In hoc libro contenta opera Hugonis de Sancto Victore. De institutione novitiorum. De operibus trium dierum. De arra anime. De laude charitatis. De modo orandi. Duplex exposito orationis dominice. De quinque septenis. De septem donis Spiritus Sancti</title> (Paris: Stephanus, 1506), fols. 87v–91r, <ref target="http://lib.ugent.be/catalog/bkt01:000321097">http://lib.ugent.be/catalog/bkt01:000321097</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note40"><title>Primo hoc Tomo Operum M. Hugonis a S. Victore contenta Epistola nuncupatoria et epigrammata, Opera tribus tomis hactenus impressa, Loca bibliorum sacrorrum ab Hugone exposita, deinde primi tomi tabula et post erratula</title> (Paris: Jodocus Badius and Johannes Parvus, 1526), fol. 211v, <ref target="http://bibliotecavirtual.larioja.org/bvrioja/i18n/consulta/registro.cmd?id=1026">http://bibliotecavirtual.larioja.org/bvrioja/i18n/consulta/registro.cmd?id=1026</ref>; Abbey of St Victor, Paris, <title>M. Hugonis de S. Victore, canonici regularis, sancti Victoris parisiensis, tum pietate, tum doctrina insignis; Opera omnia tribus tomis digesta</title> (Rouen: Berthelin, 1648), 1:303; I have been unable to consult the versions of 1588 and 1617: on the relationship between the various early-modern editions of Hugh, see Jean-Louis Quantin, <q>La réception d’Hugues et Richard de Saint-Victor au miroir de leurs <title>Opera omnia</title> (XVIe–XVIIe siècles),</q> in <title>L’école de Saint-Victor de Paris: Influence et rayonnement du Moyen Âge à l’époque moderne</title>, ed. Dominique Poirel, Bibliotheca Victorina 22 (Turnhout: Brepols, 2010), 601–42, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1484/M.BV-EB.3.4428">10.1484/M.BV-EB.3.4428</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note41">Armand-Benjamin Caillau and Benjamin Saint-Yves, eds., <title>Sancti Aurelii Augustini Hipponensis episcopi Operum supplementum I. Continens Sermones ineditos extractos ex Archivio Montis-Cassini et ex Bibliotheca Laurentiana-Medicea Florentiæ</title> (Paris: Parent-Desbarres, 1836), 160–62; their text is printed from Monte Cassino, MS 387, pp. 377–87, described in Maurus Inguanez, <title>Codicum casinensium manuscriptorum catalogus</title> (Monte Cassino, 1915–1941), 2:253.</note>
                <note xml:id="note42">Jacques Paul Migne, ed., <title>Hugonis de S. Victore, canonici regularis, Sancti Victoris Parisiensis, tum pietate, tum doctrina insignis, Opera omnia tribus tomis digesta</title>, Patrologia Latina 175–177 (Paris: Migne, 1854), 175:405–10.</note>
                <note xml:id="note43">Migne, <title>Hugonis de S. Victore Opera</title>, 175:410–14.</note>
                <note xml:id="note44">Roger Baron, ed. and trans., <title>Hugues de Saint-Victor. Six opuscules spirituels</title>, Sources chrétiennes 155 (Paris: Cerf, 1969), 100–118, introduction 30–37.</note>
                <note xml:id="note45">Baron, <title>Hugues de Saint-Victor. Six opuscules spirituels</title>, 41.</note>
                <note xml:id="note46">Monte Cassino, MS 387, as printed in Caillau and Saint-Yves, <title>Augustini Operum supplementum I</title>, 161.</note>
                <note xml:id="note47">Andrew Dunning, ed., <title>Samuel Presbiter, Notes from the School of William de Montibus: Collecta ex diuersis auditis in scola magistri Willelmi de Monte</title>, Toronto Medieval Latin Texts 33 (Toronto: Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies, 2015), 2; on William’s life and works, see Joseph W. Goering, <title>William de Montibus (c. 1140–1213): The Schools and the Literature of Pastoral Care</title>, Studies and Texts 108 (Toronto: Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies, 1992).</note>
                <note xml:id="note48">C.W. Foster and Kathleen Major, eds., <title>The Registrum Antiquissimum of the Cathedral Church of Lincoln</title>, Publications of the Lincoln Record Society 27–29, 32, 34, 41, 42, 46, 51, 62, 67, 68 (Hereford: Lincoln Record Society, 1931–1968), 4:32–33 (nos. 1140/41).</note>
                <note xml:id="note49">Foster and Major, <title>Registrum Antiquissimum</title>, 4:31 (no. 1138).</note>
                <note xml:id="note50">Goering, <title>William de Montibus</title>, 45n68; Foster and Major, <title>Registrum Antiquissimum</title>, 3:200 makes the same assumption of a Samuel Presbiter living in Huntingdon; Pipe Roll Society, ed., <title>Feet of Fines of the Tenth Year of the Reign of King Richard I, AD 1198 to AD 1199</title>, Publications of the Pipe Roll Society 24 (London: Love and Wyman, 1900), 71 (no. 104), <ref target="https://archive.org/details/piperollsociety24pipeuoft">https://archive.org/details/piperollsociety24pipeuoft</ref>, records him there in 1198.</note>
                <note xml:id="note51">Antonia Gransden, <title>A History of the Abbey of Bury St Edmunds, 1182–1256: Samson of Tottington to Edmund of Walpole</title>, Studies in the History of Medieval Religion 31 (Woodbridge, Suffolk: Boydell Press, 2007), 135–36.</note>
                <note xml:id="note52">This list is adapted from Dunning, <title>Samuel Presbiter</title>, 6.</note>
                <note xml:id="note53">Goering, <title>William de Montibus</title>, 501–3, prints the text of fol. 9r.</note>
                <note xml:id="note54">Listed alongside other works of this genre in Greti Dinkova-Bruun, <q>Biblical Versifications from Late Antiquity to the Middle of the Thirteenth Century: History or Allegory?</q> in <title>Poetry and Exegesis in Premodern Latin Christianity: The Encounter Between Classical and Christian Strategies of Interpretation</title>, ed. Willemien Otten and Karla Pollmann, Supplements to <title>Vigiliae Christianae</title> 87 (Leiden: Brill, 2007), 333, 339–40, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1163/ej.9789004160699.i-364.65">10.1163/ej.9789004160699.i-364.65</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note55">Edited in part by Greti Dinkova-Bruun, <q>Samuel Presbyter and the Glosses to His Versification of Psalm 1: An Anti-Church Invective?</q> in <title>Florilegium mediaevale: Études offertes à Jacqueline Hamesse à l’occasion de son éméritat</title>, ed. José Francisco Meirinhos and Olga Weijers, Textes et études du moyen âge 50 (Louvain-la-Neuve: Fédération Internationale des Instituts d’Études Médiévales, 2009), 157–61.</note>
                <note xml:id="note56">Unedited, but studied in Lorenzo Valgimogli, <title>Lo <title xml:lang="la">Speculum Gregorii</title> di Adalberto di Metz</title>, Archivum Gregorianum 8 (Florence: SISMEL, 2006).</note>
                <note xml:id="note57">Richard Sharpe et al., eds., <title>English Benedictine Libraries: The Shorter Catalogues</title>, Corpus of British Medieval Library Catalogues 4 (London: British Library, 1996), B13.48a.</note>
                <note xml:id="note58">Rodney M. Thomson, <title>Catalogue of the Manuscripts of Lincoln Cathedral Chapter Library</title> (Woodbridge, Suffolk: Brewer, 1989), 41 (no. 58, art. 6.18), 163 (no. 201, art. 71), 201 (no. 241, art. 9).</note>
                <note xml:id="note59">M.R. James and Ellis H. Minns, <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Pembroke College, Cambridge, with a Hand List of the Printed Books to the Year 1500</title> (Cambridge: University Press, 1905), 9, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511692796">10.1017/CBO9780511692796</ref> (no. 9), 83 (no. 90).</note>
                <note xml:id="note60">Josiah Cox Russell, <title>Dictionary of Writers of Thirteenth-Century England</title>, Bulletin of the Institute of Historical Research, Special Supplement 3 (London: Longmans, 1936), 147 (s.v. <q>Samuel Presbyter</q>).</note>
                <note xml:id="note61"><q>Qui Gulielmi de Monte celeberrimi suo tempore Oxoniae theol. professoris auditor diligens et admirator extitit.</q> Quoted in Thomas Tanner, <title xml:lang="la">Bibliotheca Britannico-Hibernica, siue, De scriptoribus, qui in Anglia, Scotia, et Hibernia ad saeculi XVII initium floruerunt, commentarius</title>, ed. David Wilkins (London: Bowyer, 1748), 651.</note>
                <note xml:id="note62">James and Minns, <title>Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Pembroke College</title>, 111–12.</note>
                <note xml:id="note63">Richard Sharpe, <q>Reconstructing the Medieval Library of Bury St Edmunds Abbey: The Lost Catalogue of Henry of Kirkstead,</q> in <title>Bury St Edmunds: Medieval Art, Architecture, Archaeology, and Economy</title>, ed. Antonia Gransden, Conference Transactions 20 (Leeds: British Archaeological Association, 1998), 214; M.R. James, <q>Bury St. Edmunds Manuscripts,</q> <title>English Historical Review</title> 41, no. 162 (April 1926): 257, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ehr/XLI.CLXII.251">10.1093/ehr/XLI.CLXII.251</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note64">M.R. James, <title>On the Abbey of S. Edmund at Bury</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge Antiquarian Society, 1895), 15–16, <ref target="https://archive.org/details/abbeyofsedmundat00jame">https://archive.org/details/abbeyofsedmundat00jame</ref>, prints Matthew Wren’s list; for a summary of the Bury library’s history, see Sharpe et al., <title>English Benedictine Libraries</title>, 43–49.</note>
                <note xml:id="note65">Listed in James and Minns, <title>Catalogue of the Manuscripts in the Library of Pembroke College</title>, pp. xx–xxiii, where it is no. 2077; this follows its enumeration in Edward Bernard, <title>Catalogi librorum manuscriptorum Angliæ et Hiberniæ in unum collecti</title>, 2 vols. (Oxford: Sheldonian Theatre, 1697), which for Pembroke reprints the listing in <hi rend="citation">Thomas James, <title>Ecloga Oxonio-Cantabrigiensis</title>, 2 vols. (London: Bishop and Norton, 1600)</hi>; R.W. Hunt, Falconer Madan, and P.D. Record, <title>A Summary Catalogue of Western Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at Oxford</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1895–1953), no. 2723, conjectures that the Bodleian Library acquired the book in 1603 or 1604.</note>
                <note xml:id="note66">Leonard E. Boyle, <q>Optimist and Recensionist: <q>Common Errors</q> or <q>Common Variations</q>?</q> in <title>Latin Script and Letters, AD 400–900: Festschrift Presented to Ludwig Bieler on the Occasion of His 70th Birthday</title>, ed. John J. O’Meara and Bernd Naumann (Leiden: Brill, 1976), 264–74.</note>
                <note xml:id="note67">Summarized by Elena Pierazzo, <q>Digital Documentary Editions and the Others,</q> <title>Scholarly Editing</title> 35 (2014), <ref target="http://scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html">http://scholarlyediting.org/2014/essays/essay.pierazzo.html</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note68">E.g. Elena Pierazzo and Peter A. Stokes, <q>Putting the Text back into Context: A Codicological Approach to Manuscript Transcription,</q> in <title>Kodikologie und Paläographie im digitalen Zeitalter/Codicology and Palaeography in the Digital Age</title>, ed. Franz Fischer, Christiane Fritze, and Georg Vogeler, vol. 2, Schriften des Instituts für Dokumentologie und Editorik 3 (Norderstedt: BoD, 2011), 397–429, <ref target="https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:hbz:38-43605">https://nbn-resolving.org/urn:nbn:de:hbz:38-43605</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note69">For another approach, see Elena Pierazzo, <q>A Rationale of Digital Documentary Editions,</q> <title>Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 26, no. 4 (December 2011): 463–77, doi:<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqr033">10.1093/llc/fqr033</ref>.</note>
                <note xml:id="note70">See M.B. Parkes, <q>Latin Autograph Manuscripts: Orthography and Punctuation,</q> in <title>Gli autografi medievali: Problemi paleografici e filologici. Atti del convegno di studio della Fondazione Ezio Franceschini, Erice, 25 settembre–2 ottobre 1990</title>, ed. Paolo Chiesa and Lucia Pinelli, Quaderni di cultura mediolatina 5 (Spoleto: Centro italiano di studi sull’alto Medioevo, 1994), 23–36.</note>
                <note xml:id="note71">E.g. Thomas Gobbitt, <q>Orthographic Preferences in the Production of Cambridge, Corpus Christi College MS 383 at the Turn of the Twelfth Century,</q> <title>Scriptorium</title> 66 (2012): 3–24.</note>
                <note xml:id="note72">Berndt, <title>Hugonis de Sancto Victore De sacramentis Christiane fidei</title>.</note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
